<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The araignement of an vnruly tongue Wherein the faults of an euill tongue are opened, the danger discouered, the remedies prescribed, for the taming of a bad tongue, the right ordering of the tongue, and the pacifying of a troubled minde against the wrongs of an euill tongue. By George Web, preacher of Gods word at Stepleashton in Wiltshire.</title>
            <author>Webbe, George, 1581-1642.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 139 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 107 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14853</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25156</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102125</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837925</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837925</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2272</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14853)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2272)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1045:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The araignement of an vnruly tongue Wherein the faults of an euill tongue are opened, the danger discouered, the remedies prescribed, for the taming of a bad tongue, the right ordering of the tongue, and the pacifying of a troubled minde against the wrongs of an euill tongue. By George Web, preacher of Gods word at Stepleashton in Wiltshire.</title>
                  <author>Webbe, George, 1581-1642.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 201, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G.P[urslowe] for Iohn Budge, and are to bee sold at his shop in Pauls church-yard, at the signe of the greene Dragon,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Print faded and show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Blasphemy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian ethics --  Anglican auhtors --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2272:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2272:1"/>
            <p>THE ARAIGNEMENT of an vnruly Tongue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>WHEREIN</hi> The Faults of an euill Tongue are opened, the danger diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, the Remedies <hi>preſcribed,</hi> FOR The taming of a bad Tongue, the right ordering of the Tongue, and the pacifying of a troubled minde againſt the wrongs of an <hi>euill Tongue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By GEORGE WEB, Preacher of Gods word at <hi>Stepleaſhton</hi> in <hi>Wiltſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. P.</hi> for <hi>Iohn Budge,</hi> and are to bee ſold at his Shop in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, at the Signe of the greene Dragon. 1619.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2272:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2272:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL Sir GABRIEL DOVSE Knight, and the right ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and worthy Lady, the Lady IOANE his wife, Increaſe of Grace, and all <hi>true Happineſſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Worſhipfull,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS petty Pamphlet (for ſo I may bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſtile it, then a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe) being ſo bold againſt the abuſes of
<pb facs="tcp:2272:3"/>the tongue, cannot but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the criticall cenſure of many a Tongue. The Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious tongue wil defame it, the Scorners Tongue deride it, the Slanderous Tongue back-bite it, the Cenſorious Tongue will whip it, the Curious toung will hang, draw, &amp; quarter it: Therefore it needeth a protecting Patronage, to giue ſome cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenance vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, againſt thoſe oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which it is likely to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming vnder the Preſſe. And what fitter Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage could it find then your two names? both which, for the Tongue, the
<pb facs="tcp:2272:3"/>one in witty ſpeech, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in diſcreet ſilence, not my ſelf alone, but diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers alſo haue held in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration. Beſides that, the neere affinity, wherewith, of late, by marriage, I am linked vnto your Family, and the many fauours vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame by you both vouchſafed vnto mee, do require this as a teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of my gratefull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of the ſame. I haue therefore preſumed to Dedicate vnto you both, a as monume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of my duty which I owe vnto you both, this poore preſent, humbly deſiring a fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb facs="tcp:2272:4"/>acceptance. Though it enrich not your coffers, yet it may your conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: for herein you ſhall finde (although vnpoliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) both an <hi>Antidote</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a bad Tongue, and an <hi>Amulet</hi> for a good Tongue; how we may bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle our owne, how wee may tame others Toungs. <hi>In many things wee ſin all:</hi> And many times wee all ſinne with this little mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, our vnruly Tongue. And what man liueth but is wronged by the tongue? Happy is that man who can auoide the ſtrife of Tongues; happier he that
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:2272:4"/>can ſet a watch before his owne tongue: A patterne for both theſe is here propoſed. God bleſſe it, both to you both, and to all that reade it. And ſo humbly crauing pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for this my boldnes, I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend you both to the Lord, and to the Word of his Grace, who is able to perfect that good worke which he hath begun in you.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips in all Chriſtian duties to be commanded, <hi>G. W.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:2272:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2272:5"/>
            <head>The Contents of the Treatiſe.</head>
            <list>
               <item>CHAP. I. <hi>THe Tongues</hi> 1. <hi>Vſe,</hi> 2. <hi>the Excellency in the Creation,</hi> 3. <hi>Miſery by Deprauation.</hi> 4. <hi>The Abuſes of it.</hi> 5. <hi>The proceeding againſt it.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>CHAP. II. <hi>The Tongue,</hi> 1. <hi>Arraigned.</hi> 2. <hi>Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of</hi> 1. <hi>High Treaſon.</hi> 2. <hi>Pettie Treaſon.</hi> 3. <hi>Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonie.</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2272:6"/>4. <hi>Murther.</hi> 5. <hi>Breach of the Peace.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>CHAP. III. <hi>The tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſsion of the Tongue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all the ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>CHAP. IIII. <hi>The Hue and Cry ſent forth againſt a naughty Tongue: a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of it.</hi> 1. <hi>From the Haunt of it.</hi> 2. <hi>From the Habit therof.</hi> 3. <hi>From the Companions.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>CHAP. V. <hi>The Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of an vnruly Tongue.</hi> 2. <hi>His Plea for himſelfe.</hi> 3. <hi>The Confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Plea.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>CHAP. VI. <hi>A delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the puniſhment
<pb facs="tcp:2272:6"/>of an euill tongue. How impoſsible it is to auoide it: How hard to endure it: How inſufficient hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane puniſhments are to tame it.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>CHAP. VII. <hi>The Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates office for the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of an euill tongue. The politike lawes of Nations, for the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment thereof.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>CHAP. VIII. <hi>The iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God againſt an euill tongue.</hi> 1. <hi>In this life.</hi> 2. <hi>In the life to come.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>CHAP. IX. <hi>The Doome, or Sentence denounced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt an euill tongue.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>CHAP. X. <hi>The binding
<pb facs="tcp:2272:7"/>of the tongue to the good behauiour. Rules and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections for the ſame.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>CHAP. XI. <hi>How we are to put off an euill tongue, when in our hearing it wrongeth others.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>CHAP. XII. <hi>How we are to endure the ſtroke of an euill tongue, when it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth our ſelues.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>CHAP. XIII. <hi>A Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the whole Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2272:7"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE</hi> ARAIGNMENT OF AN VNRVLY TONGVE.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Tongues,</hi> 1. <hi>Vſe,</hi> 2. <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation,</hi> 3. <hi>Deprauation,</hi> 4. <hi>Abuſe.</hi> 5. <hi>The procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding against it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong all the members of <hi>Mans</hi> bodie there is none
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2272:8"/>of greater vſe, none more ſubiect to abuſe then the <hi>Tongue:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Tong Iam. 3.5.</note> It is but a <hi>little member,</hi> yet a great ſtirrer in mortal affaires: of which it may bee ſaid, as ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it was of <hi>Origen, Where it is well,
<note place="margin">Vbi bene, Nemo meli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Vbi ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, Nemo pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius.</note> there none is better, where euill, nothing worſe.</hi> It is a <hi>Fountaine,</hi> whence <hi>waters flow both ſweet</hi> and <hi>bitter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 3.16, 11, 10, 8, 6.</note> It is a <hi>Forge</hi> both of <hi>Bleſſing</hi> and <hi>Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,</hi> It is a <hi>Shop</hi> both of <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Balme</hi> and <hi>deadly Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> It is the <hi>Trouchman</hi> both of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Error: Fire</hi> and <hi>Water</hi> are encloſed in it, <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> are in the power of it;
<note place="margin">Pro. 18.21:</note> It is a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2272:8"/>good, but an <hi>Vnru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly euill,</hi> very profitable, but exceeding hurtfull: wee cannot well want it, nor want woe becauſe of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> If <hi>Man</hi> had beene crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted only for GOD,
<note place="margin">The vſe of it.</note> hee ſhould not haue needed a <hi>tongue,</hi> for the Lord know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Minds meaning without the <hi>tongues</hi> narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; If he had been made for himſelfe alone, the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his mind had been ſufficient for himſelfe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a <hi>tongue</hi> to be his <hi>Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer;</hi> but God made <hi>Man a ſociable liuing creature,</hi> one <hi>Man</hi> to be a comfort vnto the other, and therefore he
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2272:9"/>had need of ſuch an Organ as the <hi>tongue</hi> to be his intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligencer and Interpreter: without a <hi>tongue</hi> we ſhould haue beene all <hi>Mutes;</hi> the <hi>pallate</hi> would haue wanted a <hi>taſter,</hi> the <hi>Mind</hi> a <hi>ſpeaker,</hi> and <hi>Man, the World of the World,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> would haue ſtood in the World but as a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Therefore the great Creator, whoſe workes are all perfect,
<note place="margin">The Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of it.</note> in the Creation did create this neceſſarie member; and placed it within the head the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal watch-towre of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. And within this Body, of our Body hath apointed
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2272:9"/>it a threefold Office, to be <hi>Taſter, Interpreter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 19.8. Iam. 1.17.</note> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trowler.</hi> God (as he is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely good, and the <hi>fountaine of all goodneſse</hi>) in the Creation made all <hi>things</hi> good,
<note place="margin">Gen. 1.27.</note> and <hi>Man</hi> moſt good, and the <hi>tongue</hi> of <hi>Man</hi> for a ſpeciall good: <hi>He ſaweuery thing that Hee had made, and behold it was good, very good.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zanc. de oper. Dei. Lib.</hi> 2.</note> The <hi>tongue</hi> was then a goodly member, full of grace, full of goodneſſe; A member wherein <hi>Man</hi> did moſt reſemble <hi>Angels</hi> exerciſe, and Gods Image; A ſweet Organ or Orga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non of delightfull ſpeech,
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.4.</note> a glorious Trumpet to ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d
<note place="margin">Pſal. 45.1.</note>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:2272:10"/>out the praiſes of the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator, a faithfull Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the <hi>hidden Man,</hi> a faire Secretarie of a moſt faire Heart; The <hi>Heart</hi> did then <hi>indite a good mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and the Tongue was the Pen of a ready Writer.</hi> Speech was then rare and precious, and the Tongue could well diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne how to bee ſilent without ſullenneſſe, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt without wantonneſſe, ſimple without ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, wittie without wickednes, conceited without offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. And in a word, the vſe and exerciſe of the Tong at that time was ſo good,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2272:10"/>that of it the <hi>encomium</hi> might bee truely giuen, which was giuen of the reſt,
<note place="margin">Gen. 1.27.</note> when they were at the beſt, <hi>It was good, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> But as <hi>Man</hi> continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not long in his Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie,
<note place="margin">The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prauation of it.</note> ſo neither the Tongue in his Integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. As in the Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of <hi>Adam,</hi> the poyſon of ſinne like a fretting canker ranne through the whole Nature of <hi>Man,</hi> ſo among the reſt of the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers it did corrupt the Tongue. And (if my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecture bee not much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued) the <hi>tong</hi> was one of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2272:11"/>firſt of the bodily mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in this corruption; ſure I am, the firſt corrupting in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument was the <hi>tongue:</hi> By the <hi>tongue</hi> of the <hi>Serpent</hi> was <hi>Eue</hi> ſeduced,
<note place="margin">Gen. 3.1, 2, 3.</note> and her <hi>tongue</hi> did ſeduce <hi>Adam;</hi> and ſince that time the <hi>tongue</hi> among our mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers hath beene the moſt vnrulieſt,
<note place="margin">Iam. 3.6.</note> 
                  <hi>defiling the whole body, and ſetting on fire the whole courſe of Nature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When ſinne had made a diuiſion betweene <hi>Man</hi> and GOD,
<note place="margin">Iſay 59.2.</note> it did diuide betweene the <hi>tongue</hi> and good, ſo that there is no greater diuiſion of <hi>tongues,</hi> then there are vices of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2272:11"/>Tongue: And though the ſubſtance of the Tongue bee not taken away by ſin, yet the quality of it is now peruerted and depraued, ſo that of a neceſſarie good, it is become <hi>an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly euill,</hi> and ſo much the more euill, becauſe it is incorrigible. The fierceſt Beaſts, the wildeſt Birds, the wilieſt Serpents are and haue been tamed by the Art of <hi>Man,</hi> but the <hi>tongue</hi> (witneſſe an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle) <hi>can no Man tame.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 3.7, 8.</note>
               </p>
               <p>If we well conſider with our ſelues the dangerous abuſes, hurts, and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniences occaſioned by
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2272:12"/>the <hi>tongue</hi> ſince this eſtate of his deprauation, it may iuſtly grow to a diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble queſtion, whether we gaine or loſe more by it? Whether there be a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter benefit of Nature, or hazard of Grace in it? For if we obſerue the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Scripture and the occurrents of times, wee ſhall meet with more miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe cauſed by the <hi>tongue,</hi> and more prayers and precepts bent againſt the abuſe of it, then againſt any other of the members ſeuerally, or all of them ioyntly.</p>
               <p>Our great Creator hath
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2272:12"/>in the fabrick of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies for the moſt part, fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vs with paires of parts, two Eyes, two Hands, two Eares, two Feet, only this one is but one, one Tong, and yet this one Tongue is more troubleſome then all the reſt. No Creature hath ſo excellent an vſe of the Tongue as <hi>Man,</hi> no Creature doth more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe, or is more abuſed by the Tongue, then <hi>Man; Halfe the ſinnes of our life</hi> (according to <hi>Nazianzen</hi> his account) <hi>are commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the tongue.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Nazianz. in deplor. ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. animae. Baſil.</hi> in Pſalme 32.</note> Baſil</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth farther, ſaying, that our whole life is full
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2272:13"/>fraught with the Tongues offences. Farther yet ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Father (and yet no farther then the truth) <hi>that there is no wrong or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie done in the world,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ambr. offic. lib.</hi> 1.</note> but first or laſt the tongue hath a ſhare in the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Againſt this vnruly Tongue,
<note place="margin">The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding a gainſt it.</note> becauſe ſo many and ſo grieuous co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaints haue been made in all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, both by Chriſtians and by the Heathens, by Diuines, Philoſophers, Poets, and all ſort of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; This preſent Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe doth intend a iudiciall proceeding, that ſo the miſdemeanors therof be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2272:13"/>diſcouered, it may at the leaſt bee bound to the good behauiour, for the better quiet of the good, and terror of the bad, when they ſhall ſee what hurt commeth by, and what danger happeneth vnto a wicked <hi>tongue.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:2272:14"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Tongue Araigned and indicted of,</hi> 1. <hi>Treaſon,</hi> 2. <hi>Fellonie,</hi> 3. <hi>Murther,</hi> 4. <hi>Riot and Routs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>FIrſt therefore we will call the malefactor to the barre,
<note place="margin">The Tong araigned.</note> that it may be examined of his abuſes, and vpon inquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it may appeare, what the cauſe is why ſo many, and that ſo often, haue been mooued to bee his accuſers, and to put in their bils of complaint a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2272:14"/>the ſame, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly it may eyther cleare his Innocencie, or elſe be found guilty.</p>
               <p>And becauſe generall accuſations (as Lawyers teach vs) will beare no Actions,
<note place="margin">The Tong indicted.</note> vnleſſe they bee confirmed by particular informations; wee will frame particular Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt this vnruly member the Tongue, and lay open (as neere as wee may) his particular miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanors. Neither ſhall wee need to ſeeke farre for matters criminall to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect againſt it, ſeeing there is no crime ſo capitall, no
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2272:15"/>offence ſo heynous, but the. Tongue is either prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall in it, or acceſſary vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> What crime is more capitall then Treaſon? And what Treaſon is there, wherin the Tongue hath not a ſhare?
<note place="margin">Of High-Treaſon againſt God.</note> Wee may indite it for <hi>High-Treaſon</hi> both againſt God and the King. Againſt GOD the Tongue is a Traitor in the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree.
<note place="margin">By Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy.</note> 1. By <hi>Blaſphemie;</hi> for ſo it is obiected againſt the rayling tongue of <hi>Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhakeh:
<note place="margin">Iſay 37.23.</note> Whom haſt thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proched and blaſphemed? Againſt whom haſt thou ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2272:15"/>thy voice? euen againſt the holy one of Iſrael.</hi> And of <hi>Antichriſts tongue</hi> it is ſaid,
<note place="margin">Reu. 13.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Hee openeth his mouth in blaſphemie againſt God, to blaſpheme his name, and his tabernacle, and them that dwell therein:</hi> And of the tongue of the ſonne of <hi>Shelomith,</hi> (whoſe blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie is recorded <hi>Leuit.</hi> 24.)
<note place="margin">Leuit. 24.</note> it is ſaid that <hi>it pierced or ſmote through the name of GOD.</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. By <hi>Idolatrie;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">By Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie.</note> for there is no Idolatrie, but the <hi>tongue</hi> is a chief Actor in it,
<note place="margin">Exo. 32.4. Hab. 2.8. Iſay 42.17.</note> either as an <hi>Herald</hi> to proclaime it, or as a <hi>Doctor</hi> to teach it, or as a <hi>Proctor</hi> to plead for it, or as a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2272:16"/>
                  <hi>Prieſt</hi> to ſacrifice vnto it? It is the <hi>tongue</hi> that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the worke of mens hands,
<note place="margin">1. Kin. 18.21.</note> 
                  <hi>Baali,</hi> It is the <hi>tongue</hi> which pleadeth for <hi>Baal,</hi> It is the <hi>tongue</hi> which with <hi>Micha</hi> crieth out for the loſſe of his <hi>Idol,
<note place="margin">Iudg. 18.24.</note> Yee haue taken away my gods.</hi> 3.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
                  <note place="margin">By Periu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</note> By <hi>Periurie</hi> likewiſe the <hi>tongue</hi> is a Traitor vnto GOD,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Henrie.</hi> 8. <hi>anno</hi> 33. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> for if it bee Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the Common-Law to counterfait the Kings Seale, and to abuſe his name to the preiudice of his Lawes, then can it bee no leſſe then Treaſon to counterfait the Priuie Seale of the King of kings,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2272:16"/>to abuſe his name to the countenancing of a lye, and to make him, as much as in it lieth, acceſſarie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to euill; yet all this (and what not?) doth a periu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>tongue,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Leuit. 19.12.</note> and therefore it is ſaid <hi>to pollute the name of GOD,</hi> and it is threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with this curſe,
<note place="margin">Deut. 5.11.</note> that it <hi>ſhall not eſcape vnpuniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now if the Tong be guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of ſuch capital Treaſon againſt God,
<note place="margin">Againſt the King.</note> no wonder if it proue a Traytor againſt the King: If it be not the Plotter, yet it is the Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of euery kind of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; next to the <hi>heart,</hi> the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2272:17"/>firſt practice of Treaſon is from the <hi>tongue;
<note place="margin">2. Sam. 20.1.</note> Sheba</hi> his <hi>tongue</hi> was the Trumpet to <hi>Iſraels</hi> rebellion. And <hi>Shinicies</hi> Treaſon was the Treaſon of the Tongue;
<note place="margin">2. Sam. 16.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Iudas</hi> did firſt betray his Maſter with his Tongue,
<note place="margin">Math. 26.14, 15.</note> before hee arreſted him with his hands. And a better <hi>Iude</hi> noteth this as a badge of a Traitor,
<note place="margin">Iude 8.11.</note> to <hi>ſpeake euill of dignities.</hi> And <hi>Korah</hi> his Treaſon is called by the ſame Author, <hi>The gaineſaying of Korah;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Wiſeman, to keep vs from the very begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of Treaſons, giueth this caueat to the Tongue,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2272:17"/>
                  <hi>Curſe not the King,
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 10.20.</note> no not in thy thoughts: For a bird of the aire wil carrie the voice, and that which hath wing ſhall diuulge it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As the Tongue hath beene indited for High-Treaſon,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
                  <note place="margin">Of Pettie Treaſon.</note> ſo in the next place wee may indite it for <hi>pettie-treaſon;</hi>
                  <note n="1" place="margin">By Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealment.</note> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by way of concealeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t againſt the King of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,
<note place="margin">Rom. 1.18.</note> 
                  <hi>in keeping backe the truth in vnrighteouſneſſe:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Clipping.</note> And by clipping the coyn of Truth,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 4.2. Pſal. 52.2, 3.</note> 
                  <hi>by louing vanitie and ſeeking after leaſing, by louing euill more then good, and lying rather then to ſpeake righteouſneſſe:</hi> And
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2272:18"/>by forging and counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fetting falſe coine,
<note place="margin">Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fetting. Pſal. 36.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Lingua concinuat dolos, It deuiſeth</hi> (or <hi>only frameth</hi>) <hi>miſchiefs, It worketh deceitfully;</hi> but alſo by Witchcraft and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret poiſonings,
<note place="margin">Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft.</note> both which in the cenſure of our Law are no leſſe then <hi>pettie-treaſons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>tongue</hi> is a <hi>Witch,</hi> for ſo the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> complayneth of the <hi>Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 3.1.</note> that <hi>they were bewit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with the gloſing toungs</hi> of their falſe teachers, and for a practiſer by poyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings,
<note place="margin">Poyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</note> Saint <hi>Iames</hi> teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of an euil Tongue that <hi>it is full of deadly poyſon;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 3.8.</note> and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:2272:18"/>the Pſalmiſt,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 58.4.</note> 
                  <hi>The poyſon of it is like the poyſon of a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent,</hi> and in another place,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 140.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Adders poyſon is vnder their lips.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The next Indictment againſt the Tongue may bee for <hi>Fellonie,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
                  <note place="margin">Of Fello<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie.</note> wherein this wretched member may euidently be conuict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for a moſt notorious malefactor; for to omit thoſe pettie Fellonies and Burglaries dayly commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the in-breaking vp the cloſet of mens ſecrets, and prying into all mens actions: the Tongue is a common <hi>pickpurſe,</hi> a noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Robber, it will not
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:2272:19"/>ſticke to robbe a man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his face, behind his backe, in the High-way, and in priuate corners, all is fiſh with it which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to the net: but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially is it guilty of a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold <hi>Fellonie.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In taking away.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1 It robbeth a man of his good name,
<note place="margin">A mans good name. Eccleſ. 7.3. Pro. 22.7.</note> 
                  <hi>which is more precious then cynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and more to bee deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red then treaſures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2 It robbeth a man of his goods,
<note place="margin">His goods. 2. Sam. 16.4.</note> as <hi>Ziba</hi> his Tongue did <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> of his lands.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3 It robbeth a man many times of his life,
<note place="margin">His life.</note> as <hi>Doegs</hi> ſlaunderous accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2272:19"/>againſt <hi>Dauid</hi> did put <hi>Dauids</hi> life oft times in hazzard, and thoſe falſe Tongues which <hi>Iezabel</hi> had ſuborned to rayſe vp falſe witneſſe againſt <hi>Naboth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Sam. 22. 1. King. 21.</note> robbed him both of his Vineyard and life in one day.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> In which reſpect wee may further indict the <hi>tongue</hi> for murther (man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaughter is too light a terme to be giuen vnto it) There is no murther like vnto the murther of the <hi>Tongue;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Of Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> of ſuch <hi>tongues</hi> the Prophet <hi>Ezechiel</hi> teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth;
<note place="margin">Ezek. 22.9</note> 
                  <hi>They carry tales to ſhed bloud.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 55.2.</note> And the Pſalmiſt
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2272:20"/>ſaith;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 55.2.</note> 
                  <hi>They cut like a Raſor,</hi> yea,
<note place="margin">Ier. 18.18.</note> 
                  <hi>They are very ſwords:</hi> Therefore <hi>Ieremies</hi> aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries did this way wreake their malice vpon the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>Come and let vs ſmite him with the tongue.</hi> An e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill <hi>tongue</hi> doth murder three at once: 1. The par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie whom he doth defame. 2. The partie vnto whom hee doth defame him. 3. Himſelfe that is the defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. And therefore doth deſcribe this bloudy <hi>tongue</hi> to bee alwayes ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with a threefold wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon,
<note place="margin">Pro. 25.18.</note> an <hi>Arrow,</hi> an <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> and a <hi>Sword;</hi> an <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row</hi> to wound the partie
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2272:20"/>whom hee would defame in his abſence whiles he is farre off; an <hi>Hammer</hi> to knocke him on the head with a falſe report vnto whome hee doth make the report: a <hi>Sword</hi> to ſtab his own Soule in commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that euill which God doth hate.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> The <hi>tongue</hi> may further be indicted for all manner of Riots, Routes,
<note place="margin">Of Riots &amp; Routes.</note> exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and miſdemeanours. 1.
<note place="margin">Quarrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</note> For a quarreller and makebate; For whence come warres and iarres, contentions and ſtrifes? doe they not commonly proceede from the <hi>tong?</hi> It
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:2272:21"/>defileth (ſaith S. <hi>Iames</hi>) the whole Body,
<note place="margin">Iam. 3.6.</note> and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth on fire the whole courſe of Nature. It is the <hi>tongue</hi> which breaketh the peace betweeue neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, giueth ſhrewd wiues ſharpe weapons to fight againſt their hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, breedes quarrels a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſeruants, and ſetteth men together by the eares:
<note place="margin">Aſſociatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> It may be indicted for aſſociation and confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracy with an euill heart: <hi>They encourage themſelues</hi> (ſaith the Pſalmiſt) <hi>in an euill matter,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 64.5.</note> they commune of laying ſnares priuately: They ſay, Who ſhall ſee them?</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:2272:21"/>It may bee indicted for a Knight of the Poſt.
<note place="margin">Knight of the Poſt.</note> It is ready to call euill good, and good euill,
<note place="margin">Eſay 5.10.</note> to put darkeneſſe for light, and light for darkeneſſe, bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for ſweete, and ſweete for bitter:
<note place="margin">Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Pro. 35.31</note> wee could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince it for a drunkard al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, for the <hi>tongue</hi> is the firſt taſter of a drunken cup, and the firſt that will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wray it ſelfe in a drunken fit. And for incontinency it hath long ſince bin pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented at the Spirituall Court, for there is no ſuch common a whore as is the <hi>tong:</hi> It wil ſuffer any who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer will, to lie with her.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:2272:22"/>It is both Pander,
<note place="margin">Inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency.</note> Bawd and Leacher, It hath the very attire of an Harlot, mentioned by <hi>Salomon, Prou.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 7.11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18.</note> 7. <hi>Shee is lewd and ſtubborne: Her feete abide not in her houſe, with an impudent face ſhe is prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to vncleaneneſſe: come, let vs take our fill of loue.</hi> Moreouer the <hi>tongue</hi> hath long agone been whipt for a vagabond or a wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring rogue:
<note place="margin">A Vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bond.</note> 
                  <hi>It goeth</hi> (ſaith the Pſalmiſt) <hi>through the earth,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 59.14 15.</note> it roueth vp and down euening and morning, and maketh a noiſe like a dogge, and wandreth vp and down grudging, if it be not ſatiſfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:2272:22"/>It hath beene taxed for a Tale-bearer,
<note place="margin">A Tale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearer. Leu. 19.16</note> 
                  <hi>wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring like a Pedler of tales among the people, Idle and yet a buſie-body,
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 3.13.</note> tattling and prattling of that which it hath nothing to doe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.</hi> It hath ſtood on the Pillory for a Cheator.
<note place="margin">A Chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. Pſal. 52.2.</note> It deuiſeth miſchiefe, and worketh deceite; In a word (that wee draw not this indictment too much beyond the ordinarie length) It is both a common Barreter,
<note place="margin">A co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon Barreter. Pro. 6.19. An incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigible member. Pſal. 12.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Sow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſcord among bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, And an incorri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible member; A Tongue that ſpeaketh proud things,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:2272:23"/>ſaying, With our tongues wee will preuaile, our lips are our owne, who is Lord o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:2272:23"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The tranſgreſsion of the tongue againſt all the ten Commandements.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>WE ſhal not need production of witneſſes for confirmation of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes,
<note place="margin">The Tongues tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> the crimes obiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted are ſo common, the miſdemeanors ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious, that they cannot bee denied. If now the Tongue ſhall goe about to trauerſe this Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſtand to the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:2272:24"/>of the Law, we may as eaſily conuict it by the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry letter of the Law; for if we examine it by the Law of Lawes, the Law of God, we ſhall finde it guiltie of the breach of euery Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute in the Law, and if wee goe through the whole Decalogue; we ſhall eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently perceiue that there is none of al the ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, but is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wayes tranſgreſſed by the Tongue.</p>
               <p>Againſt the 1.
<note place="margin">Againſt the firſt Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement.</note> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement the Tongue is a tranſgreſſor, not onely in becomming it ſelfe an Idoll (for many a mans
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:2272:24"/>Tongue is his God, whiles he doth more glorie in it, and is more confident on it, then in God) but alſo in being the common tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher and maintainer of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry, Atheiſme,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 14.1.</note> and impietie.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 115.4. Rom. 1.15. Pſal. 94.7.</note> How many a time hath the Tongue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied God? how often hath it called vpon a falſe god? who but the Tongue is a blaſphemer againſt God? what Errors or Hereſies haue there euer been, but hath beene ſet abroach by the Tongue? how often hath it tempted God? how often hath it diſhonoured him by diſtruſtfull ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches?
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:2272:25"/>how often hath it diſgraced him with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainefull ſpeeches? It is the complaint of GOD himſelfe againſt it;
<note place="margin">Mal. 3.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Your words haue beene ſtout a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt mee,</hi> Malach. 3.13. And <hi>Iob</hi> ſetteth out this diſdainefull dialect of the Tongue in this manner, <hi>They ſay vnto God,
<note place="margin">Iob. 22.14, 15</note> Depart from vs, we deſire not the knowledge of thy wayes; who is the Aimighty that wee ſhould ſerue him? and what profite ſhould wee haue if we ſhould pray vnto him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againſt the ſecond Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement the Tongue offendeth,
<note place="margin">Againſt the 2. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> by being the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:2272:25"/>factor for Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Will-worſhip. What pleadeth for <hi>Baal,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. King. 18.21.</note> but the Tongue? What a crying did it keepe for the loſſe of an <hi>Ephod, Tera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phim,</hi> and a <hi>molten Image,</hi> taken away by the <hi>Danites,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iudg. 18.23</note> from one <hi>Micha,</hi> a man of Mount <hi>Ephraim?</hi> What an Hubbub did the <hi>tongue</hi> make at <hi>Epheſus</hi> in defence of <hi>Diana,</hi> and her Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous ſeruice?
<note place="margin">Act. 19.24, 28, 32, 34.</note> It made (ſaith the Text) <hi>ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed noiſe, that ſome cryed one thing, ſome another, and at laſt there was a clamour with one voyce, about the ſpace of two houres, crying
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:2272:26"/>out, Great is Diana of the Epheſians.</hi> Neither hath the Tongue, as yet, loſt its old wont, but is ſtill a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinacious corrupter of Gods true worſhip,
<note place="margin">Deu. 12.32 Col. 2.23.</note> a maintainer of falſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, a binder of men to raſh vowes,
<note place="margin">Eccl. 5.4. Math. 15.7</note> and a diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling hypocrite, in daring to paſſe into Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence many times, without the priuity of the heart.</p>
               <p>Againſt the third Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement the Tongue offendeth,
<note place="margin">Againſt the third Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lement. Exod. 20.5</note> by taking the name of God in vaine: for how often hath it vſed the ſacred name of God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a reuerent reſpect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<note place="margin">Deu. 28 58</note>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:2272:26"/>to it; vpon the leaſt toy, and trifle which doth oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur?
<note place="margin">Deu. 32.32</note> How vainly and idly hath it often tattled of the great and waighty affaires of Religion? How many ſcurrill ieſts hath it for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged vpon the ſacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture phraſe?
<note place="margin">Eſay 66.2.</note> How forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full hath it beene to giue vnto God his due deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued praiſe?
<note place="margin">Phil. 4.6.</note> How ſlightly hath it made mention of Gods wondrous workes?
<note place="margin">Zach. 5.4. Math. 5.33 Eſay 48.1. Leu. 24.16</note> To omit the fearefull ſinne of ſwearing, forſwearing, careleſſe ſwearing, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſwearing, curſing and banning; wherein, who ſo notorious a delinquent
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:2272:27"/>as is the Tongue?</p>
               <p>Againſt the fourth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement the Tongue offendeth;
<note place="margin">Againſt the fourth Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement. Pſal. 119.13. Eccleſ. 5.1.</note> ſometimes by <hi>ſilence,</hi> when it ſhould ſpeak to the praiſe of God, ſometimes by <hi>ſpeech,</hi> by raſh vttering of prayers or prayſes vnto God: How often hath it affoorded a lip-ſeruice vnto God,
<note place="margin">Iſay. 1.14, 15.</note> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God in the mouth, when hee was not thought vpon in the heart? A ſilly Tongue that thinketh it can deceiue God with ſmooth words, crying, <hi>The Temple of the Lord,
<note place="margin">Ier. 7.4, 8.</note> the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Lord:</hi> as if all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion did but conſiſt in
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:2272:27"/>words: Whereas the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Ieremy</hi> telleth the Tongue, that in ſuch a caſe it doth but deceiue, <hi>Truſting in lying words that cannot profite.</hi> And if that bee the true ſanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Sabbath which is deſcribed vnto vs by the Prophet <hi>Eſaiah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay 58.13</note> To <hi>turne away our foot from the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, from doing our owne pleaſure vpon Gods holy day, to call the Sabbath a delight, not doing our owne waies, nor ſeeking our owne pleaſure, nor ſpeaking our own words;</hi> Then how guilty muſt the Tongue needs be of Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath profanation, which
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:2272:28"/>vpon that day doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly vtter more words of her owne then of God, and is more voluble in words of courſe then in words of grace.
<note place="margin">Col. 3.16.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And as the tongue is thus guilty of the breach of the commandements of the firſt Table,
<note place="margin">Againſt the fifth Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement.</note> ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of the ſecond. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the fift Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement it offendeth, by want of reuerence, in proud, diſdainefull, and reproachfull ſpeaking vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, or of our Superiours, Equals, &amp; Inferiours. Thus there are Tongues (fit for Eagles meate, and to bee
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:2272:28"/>food for Rauens) which <hi>mocke the father,
<note place="margin">Pro. 30.17.</note> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe the inſtruction of the mother:</hi> So there are tongues of Parents,
<note place="margin">Col. 3.21.</note> which <hi>prouoke their children vnto anger;</hi> Husbands tongues which are too bitter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their wiues;
<note place="margin">Ver. 19.</note> Wiues tongues too ſharp againſt their Husbands: Tongues of Inferiours,
<note place="margin">Exod. 4.25 Num. 16.3. Ephe. 6.9.</note> too maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy againſt their Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours; Tongues of Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours too inſulting ouer their Inferiours: To omit the many vnreuerent and vnſeemely ſpeeches which fal out many times among Equals.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:2272:29"/>
               <p> Againſt the ſixth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement the Tongue offendeth,
<note place="margin">Againſt the ſixt Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement.</note> by chiding, brawling, quarrelling, skolding, reproaching, rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and bitter ſpeaking:
<note place="margin">Math. 5.22 Eph. 4.31. Ier. 18.18.</note> For there is a murther of the Tongue, as well as a murther of the Hands; there is a ſmiting with the tongue, as well as with the hand:
<note place="margin">Pro. 12.18.</note> 
                  <hi>There is a Tongue</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) <hi>that ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth words like the pricking of a ſword.</hi> Nay, an euill Tongue doth wound dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per then any ſword; For a ſword will onely wound thoſe who come within the compaſſe of his ſtroke:
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:2272:29"/>no diſtance of place can defend from the ſtroke of an euill Tongue. A ſword can hurt onely the bodie, but an euill Tongue, both body, goods, and name.</p>
               <p>Againſt the ſeuenth Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement the Tongue offendeth,
<note place="margin">Againſt the 7. comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement.</note> by being a Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar or Bawd vnto Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe;
<note place="margin">Gen. 39.7. Eph. 5.4. 1. Cor. 15.33.</note> ſometimes by ſolliciting to vncleanneſſe; ſometimes by obſcoene &amp; filthy ſpeeches: and wee know, that <hi>euill words cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt good manners;</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by reading amorous books, ſometimes by ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing luſtfull ſongs: and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, when it doth ouerflow
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:2272:30"/>with filthy, corrupt, and vnſeemely communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Againſt the eighth Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement the Tongue offendeth;
<note place="margin">Againſt the eighth Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement.</note> by apparant ſtealth, ſtealing away mens hearts,
<note place="margin">2. Sam. 15.2.3.</note> as <hi>Abſalom</hi> did, by flatterie and aſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; and their good name,
<note place="margin">Gen. 39.14.</note> as <hi>Ioſephs</hi> Miſtreſſe did, by ſlandering and backbiting; &amp; their goods, as <hi>Gehazi</hi> did by lying:
<note place="margin">2. King. 5.22.</note> and as many a crafty Marchant daily doth, by forging, falſifying and diſſembling.
<note place="margin">Againſt the ninth Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement. Ephe. 5.3.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Againſt the ninth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement the tongue offendeth, by prating, cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:2272:30"/>lying, boaſting,
<note place="margin">Leu. 19.16 1. Sam. 22.9. 1. King. 21.12.</note> flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering, fawning, accuſing, ſlandering, tale-bearing, falſe witneſſe bearing, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing vniuſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; diuers other ſuch like practices, preiudiciall vnto peace and truth.</p>
               <p>Againſt the tenth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement the Tongue offendeth,
<note place="margin">Againſt the tenth Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement.</note> by venting forth the euil thoughts and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcences of the heart: For,
<note place="margin">Math. 15.19, 20.</note> 
                  <hi>out of the heart proceed euill thoughts, murthers, adulteries, fornications, thefts, blaſphemies, &amp;c.</hi> And theſe haue the Tongue to be their Broker.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:2272:31"/>
               <head>CHAP. IIII. </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Hue and Cry against a naughty tongue. A de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of it.</hi> 1. <hi>From its haunt.</hi> 2. <hi>From the Phyſiognomy or Habite of it.</hi> 3. <hi>From his compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THus haue we ſeene the Indictment fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med againſt the Tongue, and examining it according to the Tenor of the Law, wee finde the Bill found by the grand Inqueſt of the Prophets and Apoſtles. Now it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:2272:31"/>that wee call the offender into <hi>Coram,</hi> to ſee what hee can pleade for himſelfe; and if it bee found guilty, to receiue his reward.</p>
               <p>And to the end that our Hue and Cry may the more effectually proceed in the ſearch and inquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this ſo notorious a malefactor, we will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe him by his proper notes and characters: as namely, by the places whither moſt commonly he doth reſort, by his phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiognomie and habite, and by the company with who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he doth frequent.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:2272:32"/>
               <p> And firſt,
<note place="margin">His Haunt</note> for the place or haunt of an euil tongue, it is moſt true that he is an vbiquitary, here and there, and euery where: This lewd tongue is a daily tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueller,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 73.9.</note> 
                  <hi>It walketh through the earth:</hi> A meere <hi>Perepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tetique,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 55.10</note> Day and Night hee goeth about</hi> Citie, Court, and Countrey: yet many times,
<note place="margin">Pſa. 10.8, 9</note> 
                  <hi>He ſitteth in the lur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king places of the Villages, and lyeth in waite like a Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in his den.</hi> But the moſt proper places of his reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, are <hi>Ale-houſes, Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernes, Play-houſes, Bake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, Wooll loſts,</hi> and <hi>Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſip meetings.</hi> And he is ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:2272:32"/>if euer, abſent thence, where are any either of the family of <hi>Flatterie,</hi> or <hi>Ill-will.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for his geſture and Phyſiognomie,
<note place="margin">His ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture and Phyſiog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomie.</note> he is but <hi>a little man,</hi> or rather <hi>mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber;</hi> not very large, but a great Reacher, ſullen and cholerick in complexion; His Dialect is <hi>curſing,
<note place="margin">Iam. 3.9. Pſal. 73.9. Pſal. 10.7. Pſal. 55.21 Pſal. 52.2.</note> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit,</hi> and <hi>fraud: The words of his mouth are ſmoother then butter, but warre is in his heart.</hi> A deep <hi>Plotter,</hi> and a great <hi>Boaſter.</hi> Wee haue a full deſcription of him, <hi>Pro.</hi> 6.12.
<note place="margin">Pro. 6.12, 13, 14.</note> 
                  <hi>A naughty perſon, a froward mouth: He winketh with his eyes, he
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:2272:33"/>ſpeaketh with his feete, he teacheth with his fingers, frowardneſſe is in his heart, he deuiſeth miſchiefe conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually, he ſoweth diſcord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And for his habite,
<note place="margin">His Habit.</note> wee ſhall euer finde him ſuted with a <hi>Sword,</hi> a <hi>Raſor,</hi> with <hi>Bowe</hi> and <hi>Arrowes,</hi> and with a <hi>Boxe of Poyſon.</hi> With a <hi>Sword;</hi> for this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Tong is a <hi>ſharpe Sword: Swords are in the lips of it,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 57.4. Pſal. 59.7. Pro. 12.18. Pſal. 52.2.</note> and it ſpeaketh words like the pricking of a Sword.</hi> A <hi>Raſor</hi> it hath: for the <hi>tongue deuiſeth miſchiefe like a ſharpe raſor, working deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully.</hi> And he is an <hi>Archer</hi> alſo.
<note place="margin">Ier. 9.3.</note> 
                  <hi>The tongue is bent like
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:2272:33"/>a Bowe for lies, and lo, the wicked bend their Bowe;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 11.2.</note> they make ready their Bowe vpon the ſtring, that they may pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uily ſhoot at the vpright in heart.</hi> And there be foure principall Arrowes which it doth ſhoot forth.</p>
               <p>The 1. Arrow is Enuie, an arrow made in hell by that enuious one the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell: The feathers of this Arrow are theſe two. 1. <hi>Sadneſſe</hi> at others proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. 2. <hi>Gladneſse</hi> at the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity of other men. It is headed with the ruſtie yron of <hi>Selfe-conſuming e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 3.5.</note> and this is <hi>Sagitta venenata,</hi> an arrow full <hi>of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:2272:34"/>deadly poiſon. But</hi> (as one well taxeth it) <hi>it is but a fooles bolt ſoone ſhot,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Baſil. in Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mone de in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid a.</hi> Pro. 14.30</note> a ſhaft which more hurteth them who ſhoote with it, then thoſe at whome it is ſhot;</hi> for <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuie is the rotting of the bones.</hi> And (as <hi>Iob</hi> teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth,
<note place="margin">Iob 5.2.</note> 
                  <hi>it killeth the fooliſh, &amp; ſlaieth the Ideot.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond Arrow of an euill Tongue, is the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of <hi>Hatred,</hi> an Arrow made in hell by that old Serpent who is a murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer from the beginning.
<note place="margin">Iohn 8.44.</note> The feathers of it are <hi>Ill will</hi> and <hi>Spight:</hi> It is hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with a deſire to doe hurt.
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 18.11.</note> And this is <hi>Sagitta
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:2272:34"/>occulta,</hi> the ſecret or hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Arrow, like the Iaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin which <hi>Saul</hi> darted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Dauid,</hi> thinking therewith to haue nailed him to the wall; hee that ſhooteth it,
<note place="margin">2. Ioh. 2.11 Iam. 3.16.</note> is a manſlaier and a murtherer. And where this Arrow is in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, <hi>there is confuſion and euery euill worke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third Arrow of an euill Tongue is <hi>Mocking,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 1.1. Eph. 5.4.</note> an Arrow framed in the ſhop of the <hi>Scornefull,</hi> the feathers of it are <hi>Morologie</hi> and <hi>Eutrapelie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> ſcofs and Ieſts, it is headed with a deſire to diſgrace: and this <hi>Sagitta volans, the ſlying
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:2272:35"/>Arrow,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 91.5.</note> drawne out of the quiuer of the proud and vaineglorious, an Arrow ready vpon the ſtring in the bow of <hi>Belials</hi> childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but it ſhall fall down vpon their owne pate who are delighted in it.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 64.8.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The fourth Arrow of an euill Tongue is the Arrow of <hi>Backbiting,</hi> made by Sathan, and ſhot by Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaniſts,
<note place="margin">Reu. 12.10</note> the feathers of it are <hi>Lies</hi> and <hi>Slaunders,</hi> and it is headed with a deſire to defame. And this is <hi>Sagitta Parthica,</hi> the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thian Arrow</hi> ſhot behinde ones backe, a moſt perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Arrow to the preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:2272:35"/>of others credite and reputation, an Arrow that woundeth a farre off, and which killeth three men, the ſlaunderer, the partie ſlandered, and the receiuer of the ſlaunder with one ſtroke. And as this vnruly Tongue doth go with one of theſe foure Arrowes alwayes ready vpon his ſtring:
<note place="margin">Iam. 3.8. Pſal. 58.4.</note> So it carrieth with it a Viall full of deadly poiſon, the poiſon of it is like <hi>the poiſon of a Serpent,</hi> and that not of an ordinary ſort of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, but <hi>venenum Ptiudos:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 140.3 Deut. 32. Iob. 20.16.</note> the <hi>poiſon of Aſpes is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his lips,</hi> which kind of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:2272:36"/>poiſon is elſewhere in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scripture noted to be moſt noxious and pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</p>
               <p>Laſtly,
<note place="margin">His com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</note> the companions of an euill Tongue (for how ſhall one better bee knowne then by his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany?) are theſe:</p>
               <p>Firſt, Idleneſſe, a lazie, lowzie raſcall, which will not betake him to any la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor,
<note place="margin">Pro. 20.4.</note> by reaſon of the cold, a diſorderly liuer,
<note place="margin">2. Theſ. 3 11.</note> no wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, yet a buſie-body, and a great prater, his conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is beggery,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and his clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, Ragges.</p>
               <p>The ſecond companion of an euill Tongue, is <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice;</hi>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:2272:36"/>a mad-brain'd Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, with a ſullen look,
<note place="margin">Pro. 6.11. Pro. 23.21</note> and a fiery face, with ſuperflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of choler: He can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſpeake well,
<note place="margin">Iam. 1.21. 1. Pet. 2.1.</note> but is full of <hi>guile, diſsimulation and euill ſpeaking.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another companion of an euill Tongue is <hi>Enuie,</hi> whoſe deſcription is this: <hi>A withered bodie,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ouid. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamor. l.</hi> 2.</note> feeding vpon it ſelfe, hauing a pale face without bloud, a leane body without iuice, ſquint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eyes, black teeth, an heart full of gall, a tongue tipt with poyſon, neuer laughing but when others weep, neuer ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, but muſing vpon miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe.</hi> And this, aboue all
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:2272:37"/>other companions of an euill tongue is moſt out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious:
<note place="margin">Pro. 27.4.</note> For, <hi>Wrath is cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell, and anger raging, but who can ſtand before enuie?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another companion of an euill tongue is <hi>curioſity,</hi> a finicall fellow, of a ſpruce geſture, hauing Eagles eyes and large eares, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous euer to be acquainted with other mens euils; a buſie prier into other mens behauiour,
<note place="margin">Plutarch. de curioſnate.</note> which with <hi>Plutarchs Lamia</hi> doth put on his eyes when he goeth abroad, and layeth them aſide when he is at home. This <hi>curioſitie</hi> and an euill <hi>tongue</hi> are linked
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:2272:37"/>together by the Apoſtle as vnſeparable compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons:
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 5.13. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Pratlers and buſie-bodies, ſpeaking things which are not comely.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another companion of an euill tongue is <hi>Subtilty,</hi> an old foxe, with a warie and diſſembling gate, <hi>His throate is an open ſepulchre,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 5.9. Pſal. 55.2.</note> he flattereth with his tongue, the words of his mouth are ſofter then butter, yet warre is in his heart:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luther in Pſal.</hi> 15.3.</note> Whoſe vſuall practice (as <hi>Martin Luther</hi> noteth) is to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme himſelfe into an Angell of Light, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der fine prefaces and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious termes to back-bite.
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:2272:38"/>The cunning hypocriſy of it, and the Tongue toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is elegantly, by elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent <hi>Bernard</hi> repreſented vnto vs.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bern. in Cant. ſer.</hi> 24.</note> 
                  <hi>Some there bee</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>whoſe ſtomakes being glutted with the faults &amp; infirmities of their brethren, when they meane to diſgorge the ſame, doe ſhrowd their malice and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred vnder the cloak of feig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned reſpect, after an enforced ſigh, with great grauity, and with a well compoſed coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, they will mutter</hi> forth their ſlanderous ſpeeches. <hi>And ſuch back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitings and ſlanders</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>are ſo much the more
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:2272:38"/>dangerous, becauſe the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers are thereby occaſioned to imagine and conceiue, that the ſame proceedeth, neither of enuie, nor ill will, but out of meere ſorrow and compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another companion of an euill Tongue is, <hi>Detrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> an hungry co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panion with a biting tooth, a priuy thiefe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> anothers good name, one that laboureth to hide the good graces that are in others, and to ſuborne contrary ſurmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as the diuell did to our firſt parents concerning God,
<note place="margin">Gen. 3.9. Iob 1.9.</note> and vnto God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Iob.</hi> And this <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:2272:39"/>doth worke ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times vpon bare ſuſpition, as the children of <hi>Ammon</hi> ſlandered <hi>Dauid</hi> in the eares of their Lord <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nun,</hi> as if he had ſent Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours, vnder pretence <hi>of loue and honour,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Sam. 10.3.</note> to ſpie out the Land, and to take his Citie and deſtroy it: Sometimes without any ground at all, or ſhadow of iuſt ſuſpition, as <hi>Korah, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram</hi> did detract from <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Numb. 16.</note> accuſing them that they went about to exalt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues aboue the whole Congregation, and did take too much vpon them:
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:2272:39"/>Sometimes by relating falſe reports, as <hi>Ziba</hi> did of his Maſter <hi>Mephibo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Sam. 16.3.</note> as if hee had affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Kingdome of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, and therefore remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned behind at <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> Sometimes by miſ-repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſpeeches, or actions, in themſelues warranta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, yet wreſted to another ſenſe then they were done or ſpoken, as the falſe Witneſſes did the words of our bleſſed Sauiour,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 2.19.</note> concerning the diſſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and reparation of the Temple of his Body;
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 21. &amp; 22.9.</note> and <hi>Doeg</hi> the dealings of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> and his company with
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:2272:40"/>
                  <hi>Abimelech.</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.</p>
               <p>Another companion of an euill Tongue is <hi>Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencie;</hi> a brazen-faced ſhameleſſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panion. The Pſalmiſt compareth him to a <hi>mad dogge,
<note place="margin">Pſa. 59.3, 6</note> which run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vp &amp; down from place to place, rauing and raging, and is neuer ſatisfied:</hi> Hee hath learned of the Syco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant in <hi>Plautus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plutarch. in lib. de diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernend. amic. ab adulat.</note> to <hi>ſweare, forſweare, face and out-face any thing:</hi> and with <hi>Mede</hi> the Paraſite of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, hath propoſed vnto himſelfe this Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ime both in flattery and in infamy, to do it <hi>audacter,</hi> boldly and impudently.</p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:2272:40"/>
               <p> Theſe are the <hi>ſeuen helliſh ſpirits</hi> which an euill Tongue doth take vnto himſelfe,
<note place="margin">Luk. 11.26.</note> as his choiſeſt <hi>Companions,</hi> and with who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moſt commonly and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly hee doth conuerſe: And theſe are the moſt proper Characters and markes, whereby wee may know him and finde him out.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:2272:41"/>
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The tongues examination.</hi> 2. <hi>Plea for it ſelfe.</hi> 3. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation of this plea.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>BY this time ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing throughly pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued our Malefactor,
<note place="margin">The exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of the Tongue.</note> we haue found him out, &amp; brought him <hi>Coram,</hi> wee ſhould now proceede to his puniſhment, and to denounce the ſentence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him; but that (as <hi>Nichodemus</hi> ſomtime ſaid to the <hi>Sanhedrim</hi> of the Iewes) it might be thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:2272:41"/>againſt our proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings. <hi>Doth our law iudge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man before it heare him, and know what he hath done?</hi> Therfore that we proceed iudiciouſly, and according vnto law: Let vs call the Malefactor to the Barre, and heare him plead for himſelfe, if ſo bee hee haue any thing to ſay for himſelfe, vvhy ſentence ſhould not be denounced againſt him.</p>
               <p>Wherein wee can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect no leſſe then a cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Apologie:
<note place="margin">The Tongues firſt Plea. The ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary vſe and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiceable office of it.</note> for this ſubtill Tongue is not now to learne to tell his tale; he will pleade his neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:2272:42"/>vſe, and the good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice that hee hath done, that <hi>hee hath beene alwayes an Officer in the body corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall; leaſt idle of all the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, more ſeruiceable then all the ſences, and hath beene imployed in moſt adue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tures, as the onely Ambaſſador, Interpreter, and Orator for the Heart;</hi> But this will not ſerue his turne, for his profitable vſe cannot pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledge his abuſe; Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary ſeruants eſcape not due corrections when they offend in their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, no more may this: hath he been an Officer in the body? yet he hath not
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:2272:42"/>bin good in his office; hath <hi>hee not beene Idle?</hi> It had better many times that he had beene leſſe buſied; hath <hi>he beene ſeruiceable to the other members?</hi> he hath alſo many times wrought them much vnquietneſſe? hath he <hi>bin the hearts Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador, Orator and Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter?</hi> yet hath he not bin ſo faithfull in his imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, many a time hee hath gone before hee was ſent; many a time gone a wrong way, looking Weſtward, when hee ſhould haue gone by Eaſt; many a time hath he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued a ſubtill Orator, a
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:2272:43"/>fraudulent Ambaſſador, and a falſe Interpretour: and therfore doth deſerue to be puniſhed.</p>
               <p>Hee will further pleade the excellency of his skill,
<note place="margin">His ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Plea: The skill thereof.</note> that <hi>Hee is the onely Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſt and moſt expert Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt, the Maſter of Eloquntio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and Schoolemaſter of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation, tuner of Muſick, and teacher of the Liberall Sciences: and beſides all this, the onely Diſputant in the world for the tryall of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies.</hi> But what of all this? Is the Tongue a Linguiſt? Many times it ſpeaketh more Languages then is fit. Pleadeth he his
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:2272:43"/>facultie for <hi>Eloquence?</hi> And may hee not bee cenſured for all the <hi>Solaeciſmes, Trauliſmes, Tantologies,</hi> &amp; all other <hi>Barbariſmes</hi> in the Speech? And for the Arts, it may be wondered how the Tongue dareth to claime the ſanctuarie ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ſeeing, that beſides the Sophiſmes, errours and abſurdities which he hath foiſted into them; he hath inuented new Arts and Sciences, ſcarſe honeſt, full of craft and ſubtilties, to deceiue the world: And therefore this cannot pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledge him from the doome of iuſtice.</p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:2272:44"/>
               <p> He will reply,
<note n="3" place="margin">Plea: the cunning thereof.</note> and ſhew the miſery which would happen vnto many with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his helpe, as that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth; <hi>Wit would want a Broker, Innocencie a Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Error an Excuſer, were it not for the Tongue: Mirth would bee Mute, Boldneſſe Blanke, and Traffique a Banckrout, without the Tongue: without which alſo, poore people would be euer put to the worſt, and Women, the weaker Sexe, would want a weapon to defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</hi> But this ſerueth ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to aggrauate, then any way to extenuate the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence: for it is true indeed,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:2272:44"/>thou naughty Tongue len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ſhrewd wiues a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieuous weapon to offend their husbands; Thou ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt ſeruants againſt their Maſters, and ſetteſt neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours together by the eares; Thou art an Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>better of all quarrels, thou art that ſame <hi>Dauus</hi> which troubleſt all things: And therefore thou deſerueſt no fauour, but the very rigour of the Law.</p>
               <p>But here the Tongue is ready with another ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe; <hi>What, would you haue a man ſtand ſtill like a block, to put vp all wrongs and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries which are offered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:2272:45"/>him, and to be ſilent vpon a diſgrace? A ſilly worme when it is trod vpon will erect it ſelfe: I am a tongue, I cannot chuſe but ſpeake.</hi> But, ſirrah Tongue, who gaue you that authority? muſt you needes auenge your ſelfe? A poore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge, God wot, is the reuenge of the Tongue; yet ſeeing you are ſo ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and will needes bee medling, it is fit you ſhould be held in with bit and bridle.</p>
               <p>But,
<note n="4" place="margin">Plea; by poſting of the fault.</note> 
                  <hi>Why ſhould I bee pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed</hi> (ſaith the Tongue) <hi>who, if I do offend, the fault is not mine, but theirs who
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:2272:45"/>do abuſe mee, I am but an organon or inſtrument; if there be a fault in mee, their fault is the greater who make me faulty.</hi> True indeed; but yet in matters of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence the acceſſarie is lya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to offence as well as the principall: The Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent was but the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment abuſed by Sathan to deceiue man, yet in the puniſhment the Serpent hath his doome as well as Sathan.</p>
               <p>Here the conuicted Tongue hath no more to ſay,
<note n="5" place="margin">Plea; by entreatie.</note> but from Apologie falleth to Entreatie: <hi>Hee hath often pleaded for
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:2272:46"/>others, and begged their pardon, hopeth to obtaine fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour now for himſelfe, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially promiſing reformation for the time to come.</hi> But it is well knowne, that this delinquent hath beene of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in this offence; Beſides that, it can equiuocate, diſſemble, lye, promiſe much, but performe little; and therefore there is no mercyto be ſhewed, where no amendment can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected.</p>
               <p>What now can this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly Tongue plead for it ſelfe,
<note place="margin">The exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the tongu from all benefite of the Law.</note> vnleſſe (which is the laſt refuge of conuicted Felons) it claime the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:2272:46"/>of his Clergie? But as for that he can haue no hope; for beſides that the Law doth exempt ſuch no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious and capitall offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders from the benefite of their book, it is welknown, that the Tongue hath moſt offended againſt the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, to whom, albeit the Tongue is moſt behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, yet none are more then they traduced and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed by the Tongue.</p>
               <p>Wherfore, ſeeing this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly member hath no iuſt Apologie, by which it may plead for it ſelfe, nor can alleage any reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble exception, why the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:2272:47"/>cenſure of iuſtice ſhould not paſſe vpon it, let it ſtand by and heare his Doome.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:2272:47"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A deliberation for the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of an euill tong. How impoſſible it is to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void it. How grieuous to endure it How inſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient all earthly puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are to tame it. The proper puniſhment by the lawof God allotted vnto it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHat ſhall bee gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto thee?
<note place="margin">A delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration for the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of a falſe Tongue.</note> what ſhal be done vnto thee, thou falſe tongue?</hi> Harſh it is to endure, hard to tame, impoſſible to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoid
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:2272:48"/>thee: Nor man, nor meanes can preuent thee, for let a man bee as faithfull as <hi>Abraham,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 18.19. Gen. 26. Gen. 27. 1. Sam. 12.2. Iohn 1.47.</note> as ſimple as <hi>Iſaac,</hi> as ſubtill as <hi>Iaacob,</hi> as innocent as <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel,</hi> as vpright as <hi>Dauid,</hi> as ſincere as <hi>Nathaniel:</hi> yet hee cannot poſſible a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoid the laſh of an euill Tongue; though a man vſe all the policy in the world, he cannot preuent it. Though hee ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue with <hi>Dauid,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 55.6, 7, 8. How im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to auoid it.</note> O that I had wings like a Doue, for then I would flee away and bee at reſt, loe, then I would flee away and bee at reſt, I would wander farre off and
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:2272:48"/>remaine in the wilderneſſe,</hi> yet could hee not eſcape from this ſtorme, winde,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 139.9</note> and tempeſt: Though <hi>a man take the wings of the morning, and dwell in the vtmoſt parts of the ſea,</hi> yet thither would an euill Tong flye after him, euen ſo farre off would it reach him. There is no poiſon ſo venemous but there may be ſome Antidot againſt it. But there is no Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dot againſt the venim of the Tong; There is no fire ſo raging, but that ſome kinde of moiſture may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh it. The fire of an euill Tongue is like the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:2272:49"/>fire of hell which goeth neuer out.</p>
               <p>The Arrow which is ſhot out of the ſtrongeſt Bow, and ſent forth with the greateſt force, can hurt no farther then it can reach. But let a man bee neuer ſo farre off, let him bee beyond the Seas, let him be in neuer ſo farre re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Regions, and diſtant Countryes, the Arrow of an euill Tongue wil reach him and wound his good name; other weapons one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hurt the preſent, this hurteth thoſe alſo who are abſent; there is none that can bee priuiledged from
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:2272:49"/>its ſtroke.</p>
               <p>As none can auoid it,
<note place="margin">How hard it is to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure it.</note> ſo who can well beare it? fleſh and bloud can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly brooke it; If a man had the meekneſſe of <hi>Moſes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Num. 12.3 Iob. 1.21. Iam. 5.11. Iud. 15.15. Pſal. 69.20 1. King. 3.</note> the patience of <hi>Iob,</hi> the ſtrength of <hi>Samſon,</hi> the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of <hi>Dauid,</hi> and the wiſedome of <hi>Salomon:</hi> yet of himſelfe were he neuer able to endure the vnceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant wrongs by an euill Tongue; for <hi>a good name is better then a precious oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7.1. Pro. 22.1.</note> and more to be deſired then great riches, yea, then ſiluer and gold;</hi> who can brooke the impeachment of this? Other wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds may
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:2272:50"/>be cured, other loſſes may be recouerd, but this is a wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d which can neuer be healed, a loſſe which can neuer be recouered. And therfore there is no ſmart like to the ſmart of the Tong: the words of it are deuouring words,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 52.4. Pro. 11.18. Pro. 26.22.</note> 
                  <hi>They are like to the pricking of ſwords,</hi> yea, <hi>They are wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, &amp; they go down to the inner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Chambers of the bellie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet what remedy can there bee deuiſed againſt it?
<note place="margin">The diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of taming of it.</note> what penalty to inflict vpon it? what Art to tame it? let a man haue the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage of <hi>Caleb,</hi> the policy of <hi>Achitophel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Num. 14.8</note> the ſeuerity of
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:2272:50"/>
                  <hi>Iehu,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Sam. 16.20. 2. King. 10.17. Exod. 1.10</note> the cunning of <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh,</hi> the cruelty of <hi>Phalaris</hi> the inuention of <hi>Perillus,</hi> yet he ſhall not be able to tame an vnruly Toung, or reforme this incorrigible monſter:
<note place="margin">Pro. 14.4.</note> for the <hi>words of a mans mouth are as deep wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> who can ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? who can hope to exhauſt them? A Toung enraged <hi>is harder to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med;
<note place="margin">Pro. 18.19.</note> than a ſtrong City is to be conquered. The contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of it, are like the barres of a Caſtle.</hi> How plainley and pregnantly doth the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Iames</hi> demonſtrate this! firſt he ſheweth that it is eaſier to tame a wilde
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:2272:51"/>
                  <hi>horſe</hi> then a wild <hi>Tongue. We put bits</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes mouthes that they may o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey vs;
<note place="margin">Iames 3.3.</note> and wee turne about their whole body:
<note place="margin">verſe 4.</note> but the</hi> Tongue <hi>can no man tame.</hi> Then he doth inſtance in the Ships, which although they are great bulks, &amp; are <hi>driuen with fierce winds,
<note place="margin">verſe 7, 8.</note> yet can be ruled &amp; turned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with a little rudder or helme:</hi> But the Tongue, a little member, can no man rule or order. Then hee inſtanceth in Beaſts, Birds, and Serpents, which although they bee fierce, and wild and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till, yet <hi>they are, and haue
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:2272:51"/>beene tamed by the Art of man: but the tongue can no man tame, it is an vnruly euill, full of deadly poyſon.</hi> And therefore the very Heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did acknowledge, that <hi>contra Sycophanti morſum nullum eſt remedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um: There is no remedy or cure, againſt the biting of an euill Tongue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What then ſhall bee giuen vnto thee?
<note place="margin">The ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornneſſe of it.</note> what ſhall be done vnto thee, thou falſe Tongue? There is no <hi>Balme</hi> will ſupple it, for an euill tongue will <hi>reward euill for good,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 35.11</note> and like a nettle, the more gently it is touched, the more
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:2272:52"/>ſharply it will ſting. There is no charme can charme it, for what is commonly ſaid of the Belly, <hi>Venter non habet aures; The belly hath none eares,</hi> may bee as truely verified of the Tongue, <hi>Lingua non habet aures, the tongue hath no eares.</hi> And although they who haue this euil tongue, haue eares as well as tongue; yet, as they imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the poyſon of the <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> in their Tongue, ſo they haue the deafeneſſe of the <hi>Adder</hi> in the Eare:
<note place="margin">Pſa. 58.4, 5</note> 
                  <hi>They are like the deafe Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which ſtoppeth her eare, and will not hearken to the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:2272:52"/>voyce of the Charmer, char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming neuer ſo expertly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What then ſhall wee do to tame this vnruly member?
<note place="margin">The inſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency of earthly puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it.</note> Shall we binde it to the good behauiour? It neuer had it, and is out of hope now to bee brought vnto it. Shall wee make his <hi>Mittimus</hi> and ſend him to the Iayle, to ſee whether impriſonment will reclaime it? There are no lockes able enough to keepe him in, no ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſtrong enough to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnare it. The Head, the Hands, the Feete, may be impriſoned, but the Tong cannot be impriſoned; no,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:2272:53"/>though it be put in <hi>Herods</hi> priſon, and watched with foure Quaternions of Souldiers,
<note place="margin">Act. 12.4.</note> it will breake priſon, and walke at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: For, it is well knowne, that although it be kept in with a double dore of lips, and within that hath two perculleiſes of Teethen grates to enuiron it, yet it will eſcape and range a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad. Shall we doome it to the whip? It will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerberate laſh for laſh, and bee ſure to put him to the worſt that ſhall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture to meddle with it. Shall we burne him in the hand, and ſeare him with
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:2272:53"/>the letter <hi>Tau?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 3.6.</note> It will <hi>ſet on fire the whole courſe of nature, it ſelfe being ſet on fire of hell.</hi> Shall we drown him? All the water in the Sea will not waſh away its pollution. Shall we hang, draw and quarter him? So it hath done many an ones good name. But where ſhall wee finde a Gallowes or Gibbet high enough for the ſame? Shall wee behead him? So long as it is able to wagge, it will neuer ceaſe to ſpeake.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What then ſhalbe giuen vnto thee? What ſhall be don vnto thee, thou falſe tongue?</hi> Surely, no other thing
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:2272:54"/>then that which <hi>Dauid</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the like deliberation doth deliuer,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 120.</note> 
                  <hi>Sharpe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes of the Mighty with coales of Iuniper.</hi> Where by the Mighty we may ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnderſtand the Lord <hi>of Hoſts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Wolphius.</note> who is <hi>the Lord ſtrong and mighty,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 24.8.</note> the Lord mighty in battell,</hi> the Magiſtrates, who is the Lords;
<note place="margin">Molerus.</note> Deputy? <hi>a man of might:</hi> And by the ſharpe Arrowes and Iuniper coales, wee are to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the ſharpe puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments &amp; dreadfull iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which either the Magiſtrate in the courſe of Law, or God Almighty
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:2272:54"/>in his moſt iuſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment doth inflict vpon an euill Tong. Here then we are to take notice; firſt, of the law of Nations againſt an euill Tongue. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, of Gods ſecret iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Firſt, of the tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall. Secondly, of the eternall puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which do belong vnto the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:2272:55"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Magiſtrates Office for the puniſhment of a naughty tongue.</hi> 2. <hi>The politike lawes of Nations for the taming of the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THAT the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate by his autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is to take or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der againſt an euill Tou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g,
<note place="margin">The Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates Office for to puniſh a naughty Tongue.</note> and vvith ſeuerity to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the ſame, it is as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent as the Sunne; for he is <hi>a man of might,</hi> he ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <hi>in the Seat of God to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute
<note place="margin">Pſal. 82.1.</note>
                     <pb n="97" facs="tcp:2272:55"/>the iudgements of God,
<note place="margin">2. Chro. 19.6. Rom. 13.4.</note> he beareth not the ſword in vaine, but is to execute ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance vpon euill dooers: Neither only vpon euill doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, but vpon euill ſpeakers alſo,</hi> as vpon lyers, raylers, backbiters and ſlanderers: for ſo <hi>Dauid</hi> doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe of his practice in ſuch an Office,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 101.5</note> 
                  <hi>whoſo priuily ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth his neighbour, him will I cut off.</hi> Hee inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not a puniſhment onely for the periured tongue, and publique de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famer, but alſo for the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret calumniator and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie ſlanderer, neither is it a check or pettie puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:2272:56"/>which hee doth threaten againſt it,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificat ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminare, ſeu conſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendo &amp; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arctando diſperdere.</hi>
                  </note> as to baniſh it his Court, to puniſh it by the purſe, or to inflict a ſlight puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vpon it; but he would euen cut it off, roote it out and vtterly deſtroy it.</p>
               <p>The lawes of Nations haue beene diuers,
<note place="margin">Politike Lawes of Nations for the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof.</note> yet all dreadfull for the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of an euill Tongue. The <hi>Iudiciall</hi> law giuen by God <hi>himſelfe vnto the Iewes,</hi> (and therefore the beſt patterne for all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane lawes) did thus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed againſt it:
<note place="margin">Deut. 19.16, 17, 18, 19, 20.</note> 
                  <hi>If a falſe witneſse riſe vp againſt any man, to teſtifie againſt him
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:2272:56"/>that which is wrong, then both the men betweene whom the controuerſie was, were to ſtand before the Lord, before the Prieſts, and the Iudges which were in thoſe dayes: And the Iudges were to make diligent inquiſition. And if the witneſſe were proued falſe, that his tongue had teſtified falſely againſt his Brother, then the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe which hee had thought to haue done againſt his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, was to light vpon his owne head, and hee was ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerely to bee puniſhed</hi> ad terrorem aliorum, <hi>for the feare and terrour of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:2272:57"/>
               <p> And leſt wee ſhould thinke this Iudiciall courſe to be limitted onely to a falſe Witneſſe, and to a periured Tongue, the Wiſe-man,
<note place="margin">Pro. 19.5, 9</note> 
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 19.5, 9. doth extend it to all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of iniuries committed by the Tongue. <hi>A falſe witneſſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſhall not be vnpuniſhed, and hee that ſpeaketh lies, ſhall not eſcape.</hi> And to this Iudiciarie courſe of proceeding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt an euill tongue, our bleſſed Sauiour doth ſeem to allude,
<note place="margin">Math. 5.22.</note> 
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 5.22. when hee ſaith; <hi>Whoſoeuer is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with his brother without a cauſe, ſhall be in danger of
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:2272:57"/>iudgement, and whoſoeuer ſhall ſay vnto his brother, Racha, ſhall be in danger of the Councell.</hi> Where, vnder that one word <hi>(Racha)</hi> he doth vnderſtand all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of opprobrious ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and diſdainefull ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures: and by the termes of <hi>Iudgement, Councell,</hi> and <hi>Hell fire</hi> there mentioned, hee doth glaunſe at the three Courts of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Betram. de Polit. Iud. c.</hi> 13.</note> The firſt whereof was for the determining of matters litigious about wealth and poſſeſsions, and in that were three Iudges. The ſecond for matters crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:2272:58"/>which were iudged by a Councell of three and twenty. The third, for matters of more ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous weight and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, to bee determined by the <hi>Sanhedrim,</hi> or great Councell of ſeuenty and one. And in theſe Courts the Iewes (as <hi>Druſius</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lateth) did thus proceed againſt ſuch as offend with the tongue: firſt, they had priuate, and after that more publike admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to refraine from that wicked courſe: if this could not preuaile, they were excommunicate fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Synagogue: if this
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:2272:58"/>would not ſerue to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme them, they were further excommunicated from all ſociety and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of other men: if this would not reſtraine them, the great <hi>Anathema Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranatha</hi> was denounced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them: If yet they proceeded in their euill, they were iudged worthy to be ſtoned to death.</p>
               <p>Leauing the Iudiciall Law of the Iewes, come we to the Lawes of Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and wee ſhall finde, how in all Ages, &amp; among all Nations, there haue euer beene ſharpe puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments prouided againſt
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:2272:59"/>ſhrewd Tongues. The <hi>Grecians</hi> (as <hi>Thucidides</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth) were wont to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the lauiſh Tattling of the Tongue with laſhes of roddes, whipping the whole body. The <hi>Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> (as <hi>Polybius</hi> recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth) did boare an hole thorow an vnruly tongue. The <hi>Perſians</hi> (ſaith <hi>Strabo</hi>) made them ſlaues, who could not be Maſters ouer their Tongues. The <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> (as <hi>Acosta</hi> noteth) did exclude ſuch as had vnru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Tongues,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acoſta lib.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 9.</note> from all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Suidas in Canopo. Ruffin. hiſt. eccl. lib.</hi> 2.</note> The <hi>Chaldeans</hi> (as <hi>Suidas</hi> obſerueth) did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne them to perpetuall
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:2272:59"/>darkeneſſe.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Euſebius l.</hi> 5 <hi>c.</hi> 21.</note> The <hi>Romanes</hi> (as <hi>Euſebius</hi> teſtifieth) had a Lawe to breake the legs of him who had a naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty tongue; which cuſtome was put in execution (as <hi>Nicephorus</hi> relateth) in the time of the raigne of the Emperour <hi>Commodus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Niceph. l.</hi> 4.26.</note> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a prophane wretch who had ſlandered <hi>Apollo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> a godly Profeſſor, and afterwards a bleſſed Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr; The ill tongu'd accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, not being able to proue his allegations, was iudged to haue his legges broken, becauſe he had ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, and defamed a man without a cauſe. <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodotus</hi>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:2272:60"/>maketh mention of a Lieutenant of King <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Herodot. in Clio.</note> who cauſed one of his Souldiers to bee put to death, for that his tongue had beene too lauiſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Alexander,</hi> though an enemy. And hee rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth another Hiſtorie of <hi>Antigonus,</hi> who impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a foule-mouthed Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant in a Cage, depriuing the whole body of liberty, becauſe of the too much liberty of the Tongue. <hi>Leontius</hi> the Emperour (as Sir <hi>Martin Cognet</hi> in his Politike diſcourſes doth deliuer) after he had put <hi>Iustinian</hi> to flight,
<note place="margin">Politike diſcourſe of Sir <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tin Cognet.</hi> c. 37.</note> cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:2272:60"/>two of his Tale-bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers to bee trailed by the heeles and to be burned. The Emperour <hi>Pertinax</hi> cauſed the skinnes of ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers to bee flaied from their Bodies: and <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus</hi> another Emperour tooke order to haue the Tongues of vnruly railers to be pulled out of their mouthes.</p>
               <p>Excellent were thoſe Lawes, which <hi>Titus, Ner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua,</hi> and <hi>Traian</hi> (as <hi>Sueto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> writeth) made againſt tattling Tongues, the leaſt mulct wherein was whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping cheere. <hi>Domitian, Anthony,</hi> and <hi>Macrinus</hi>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:2272:61"/>baniſhed them the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines of the Empire, yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this for their reaſon, that they <hi>who did not puniſh them,
<note place="margin">L. praeuar. de verb. Leg. tit. ad Segnat.</note> did encourage them.</hi> The Ciuill Law in like maner doth inflict baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to an euill Tongue: The Canon Law doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar it from the receiuing of the Sacraments: The Common Law of this our Land doth adiudge the falſe tongue to the Pillory,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Weſtm.</hi> 1. <hi>ca</hi> 23. <hi>Kech.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 7.</note> the skolding Tongue to the Tumbrell, or Cucking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoole; the railing Tongue to the good behauiour; the ſlanderous Tongue, if it be <hi>Scandalum Magnatum,</hi> to
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:2272:61"/>the loſſe of an eare; if againſt a priuate perſon, to the cenſure of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, according to the quality of the offence.</p>
               <p>Thus wee ſee how odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous among all Nations an euill Tongue hath alwaies bene, and what ſtrict Lawes from time to time, haue bene enacted againſt the ſame. But becauſe theſe good Lawes are not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies put in execution, &amp; the Magiſtrate may proue many times remiſſe, let vs proceed further to behold a more diſmall doome from a greater Iudge, the iudgement of almighty
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:2272:62"/>God, and the fearefull puniſhments which he doth inflict vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an euill Tongue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:2272:62"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII. </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Iudgements of God againſt an euill Tongue.</hi> 1. <hi>In this life.</hi> 2. <hi>In the life to come.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHO is ſo migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as the Lord?
<note place="margin">God will ſurely pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill toung. Ex. 15.12. Pſal. 75.7. Iam. 4.2. Pſal. 9.16.</note> Who is like vnto him? glorious in holineſſe, fearefull in his workes, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wonders?</hi> Hee is the Iudge: yea that great Iudge, which can ſaue and can deſtroy: yea, <hi>Hee is knowne by the iudgement which he executeth:</hi> And among the reſt of his
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:2272:63"/>iudgements this is one of the moſt remarkeable, his puniſhments againſt an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill Tongue: For hee him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe hath vndertaken the cenſure of it; Hee hath proteſted that hee will come <hi>a ſwift witneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mal. 3.5.</note> He hath ſworne that <hi>vengeance is his,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 10.30</note> and <hi>Hee will repay it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The iudgements of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God againſt an euill Tongue, are of two ſorts (according to that which before was noted out of the Pſalmiſt) <hi>Sharp Arrowes, and coales of Iuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per:</hi> The firſt ſort Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall puniſhments; the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:2272:63"/>ſort eternall: The firſt for this life; the ſecond for the life to come.</p>
               <p>Euen in this world the Lord will not ſuffer a naughty tongue to go vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed: For,
<note place="margin">Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in this life a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt an euill tongue. Pſal. 11.2.</note> as wicked tongued people <hi>doe bend their Bowe, and make ready their Arrow vpon the ſtring, that they may priuily ſhoote at the vpright in heart;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 7.12, 13.</note> So God aboue doth <hi>bend his Bowe and make it readie: Hee prepareth for them the inſtruments of death: Hee ordaineth his Arrowes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch kinde of perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors.</hi> Let vs take a view of ſome of thoſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:2272:64"/>which God euen in this world, doth ſhoote a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt wicked and malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Tongues.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt Arrow which God doth ſhoote againſt thoſe who ſhoot at others with their Tongues,
<note place="margin">Gods Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt euil Tongues.</note> is their owne Arrow,
<note place="margin">Diſgrace.</note> the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of Diſgrace: <hi>Their owne tongue</hi> (ſaith the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt) <hi>ſhall fall vpon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 64.8.</note>
                  <note place="margin">Pſ. 7.15, 16</note> And againe, <hi>He hath made a pit, and digged it, and is fallen into the Ditch which he made: his miſchiefe ſhall returne vpon his owne head, and his vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent dealing ſhall come vpon his owne pate.</hi> And againe,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:2272:64"/>
                  <hi>Theſe wicked people are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnared in the worke of their owne hands.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 9.16.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond Arrow di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected againſt an euill Tongue,
<note place="margin">Pouerty.</note> is <hi>Pouertie;
<note place="margin">Pro. 14.23.</note> In all labour</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) <hi>there is profite, but the talke of the lips tendeth to pouerty.</hi> And who ſeeth not that this curſe ſticketh cloſe to thoſe that haue euill Tongues;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 59.15</note> That <hi>they wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vp and downe begging their bread;
<note place="margin">Pſ. 109.10.</note> their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren alſo proue vagabonds and beggars, and ſeeke their bread out of deſolate places?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third Arrow which
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:2272:65"/>the Lord ſhooteth againſt an euill Tongue is <hi>Miſery:</hi> for the Pſalmiſt plainely telleth thoſe who abuſe their Tongue,
<note place="margin">Miſery.</note> 
                  <hi>that GOD doth heare them and will af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict them.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 55.19</note> Pſal.</hi> 55.19. And <hi>Salomon</hi> ſheweth them, what muſt bee their ſole expectation. <hi>Hee that hath a peruerſe tongue, falleth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to miſchiefe.
<note place="margin">Pro. 17.20 &amp; 14.</note> Prou.</hi> 17.20. hee may neuer looke for quietneſſe and peace, for his Tongue of ſtrife will <hi>be like a continuall water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breach.
<note place="margin">Pro. 4.17.</note> Prou.</hi> 17.14. Hee can neuer take comfort in his foode, for <hi>he eateth the bread of wickedneſſe, and
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:2272:65"/>drinketh the wine of vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. Prou.</hi> 4.17. He can neuer hope to bee eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed:
<note place="margin">Pro. 26.28</note> for <hi>a falſe tongue wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth ruine.</hi> Hee can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be in ſafety, for he car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth about with him al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies a guilty conſcience. The <hi>flying Arrow of Gods iudgement is euer ready to fall vpon his pate:
<note place="margin">Iob. 15.21. Pſal. 11.6. Pſal. 52.5.</note> the Lord will raigne ſnares, fire and brimſtone, and horrible tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt, this ſhall be the portion of their cup. God will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them for euer, hee will take them and pluck them out of their tabernacle, and roote them out of the Land of the liuing.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:2272:66"/>
               <p> Infinite are the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples which wee may reade in hiſtories both diuine &amp; humane,
<note place="margin">Examples of Gods iudgement vpon euill Tongues.</note> of Gods dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full iudgements vpon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill Tongues: for the lying Tongue, wee haue in the Scriptures the example of <hi>Gehezi,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. King. 5.27.</note> ſtrucken with le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie, both himſelfe and all his poſterity.
<note place="margin">Act. 5.5, 10</note> 
                  <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> his wife, for the ſame fault ſtrucke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with ſudden death; in humane Hiſtories wee reade how wormes did eate out the lying tongue of <hi>Nestorius;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Nicephorus.</note> and <hi>Popiel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Monſtrelus.</note> King of <hi>Polonia,</hi> an accuſtomable lyer, ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten out with Rats. For the
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:2272:66"/>ſwearing and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Tongue, we haue in ſacred Scriptures a blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer ſtoned to death with ſtones,
<note place="margin">Leuit. 24.23.</note>
                  <note place="margin">2. King. 19</note> 
                  <hi>Zenache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribs</hi> Armie deſtroyed in one night by the peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and himſelfe ſlaine by his owne ſonnes in the Temple of his Idols for the ſame offence. In Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall Hiſtories wee reade of an Arrow (ſent as it is ſuppoſed,
<note place="margin">Socrates Eccl. hiſt.</note> from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen) wounding to death blaſphemous <hi>Iulian:</hi> of <hi>Michael</hi> a Iewiſh Rabbin, breaking his neck downe a paire of ſtaires, euen then whiles hee was ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:2272:67"/>and blaſpheming the name of Ieſus.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Fincilius de mirac. lib.</hi> 2.</note> And of a ſwearing Courtier at <hi>Mansfield,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Spangeb. in elegantiis ve teris Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi.</note> in the midſt of his blaſphemous oathes taken vp and carried away by the Diuel. To omit that which our owne Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles do record of <hi>Alphred,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stow in vit. Adelſtan. Jdem in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Alfredi. Jdem in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Elizah. Act. &amp; Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num. pag.</hi> 2101. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2105.</note> of Earle <hi>Godwin,</hi> of <hi>Anne Aueries,</hi> of the Gentleman of <hi>Cornewall,</hi> who being v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſwearing and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous ſpeeches, as hee was riding ouer a bridge, his horſe ſprang ouer with him on his backe into the riuer where he was drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, hauing no other words in his mouth for
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:2272:67"/>his laſt farewell, but theſe, <hi>Horſe and man and all to the Diuell.</hi> For the ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous and backbiting Tongue we haue likewiſe many examples of Gods great and fearefull iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: In the ſacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures we reade of wicked <hi>Iezabel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. King. 9.36.</note> for her falſe accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of <hi>Naboth,</hi> deuoured by dogs:
<note place="margin">Heſt. 7.10.</note> of <hi>Haman</hi> han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged vpon the Gallowes, for his falſe accnſing of the Iewes:
<note place="margin">Dan. 6.</note> of <hi>Daniels</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſers deuoured by Lions, becauſe of their falſe ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions. In the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall Hiſtories we reade of feareful iudgements of
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:2272:68"/>God vpon three ſlande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous traducers of <hi>Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Niceph. lib.</hi> 9</note> The one of whome was preſently ſtricke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dead, the others eyes fell out of his head, the third periſhed with a fearefull burning within his entrales. In our owne Chronicles we read of <hi>Thomas Arundel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act. &amp; Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num. pag.</hi> 700.</note> who hauing abuſed his Toung to an vniuſt ſentence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lord <hi>Cobham,</hi> was ſtricken with ſo ſore a paine and ſwelling in his Tongue, that he could nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſwallow nor ſpeake. So of Iuſtice <hi>Morgan,</hi> for his raſh proceedings in ſpeech againſt the Lady
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:2272:68"/>
                  <hi>Iane,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid. pag.</hi> 1912.</note> we read that he was ſtricken with madneſſe, and a little before his death had none other word but her name in his mouth. The like fearefull iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t we read to haue befallen one <hi>William Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> in Q. <hi>Maries</hi> dayes,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jbid.</hi> 1907.</note> who, for greedineſſe to gaine the goods of one <hi>Iohn Cooper,</hi> had ſlande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly accuſed him of traitrous words by him ſpoken againſt his Prince: by which the poore inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent man was condemned to death as in caſes of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: but the iudgement of God ſhortly ſeaſed vpon
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:2272:69"/>his falſe accuſer, ſtriking him, euen whiles hee was well &amp; luſty, with a ſudden diſeaſe in his belly, ſo that his bowels guſhed out.</p>
               <p>Infinite are the like ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of Gods dreadfull iudgements vpon euill tongues, euen in this life. But if any wretched toung ſhall ſet light by theſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they do not befall al them who offend in this kind, yet let them feare and tremble at thoſe feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full finall torments which GOD hath prepared for theſe offenſiue Tongues after this life, from which it is impoſſible for any of
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:2272:69"/>them to eſcape without repentance.</p>
               <p>For as God hath Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes heere to wound an euill Tongue:
<note place="margin">Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this life vpon an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill toung.</note> So hath he Coales hereafter to burne an euill tongue. The Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes indeed are ſharpe; for they are the Arrowes of the Mighty: But the Coales are more terrible; for they be Iuniper coales of long continuance, of perpetuity. Theſe coales are the fire of Hell, the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured portion of a wicked Tongue: for ſo S.
<note place="margin">Iam. 3.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith, that it is <hi>ſet on fire of hell,</hi> and therefore it ſhall to the fire in Hell; It is the
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:2272:70"/>verdict of our Sauiour, that the railing tongue is in danger of <hi>Hell fire, Mat.</hi> 5.22.
<note place="margin">Math. 5.22 Pſal. 9.17.</note> So ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>They ſhall bee turned into hell.</hi> So the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> 2.
<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 1.9</note> 
                  <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.9. <hi>They ſhall bee puniſhed with euerlaſting de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction from the preſence of the Lord.</hi> And of them the Apoſtle <hi>Iude</hi> teſtifieth,
<note place="margin">Iude 13. &amp; 15.</note> That <hi>to theſe raging waues, foming out their owne ſhame, is reſerued the blackneſse of darkeneſſe for euer.</hi> And againe, <hi>The Lord will come with ten thouſand of his Saints, to execute iudgement vpon them, and to puniſh them;</hi> not onely for their
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:2272:70"/>vngodly words, but alſo for their hard and hatefull ſpeeches. And it is well worth the noting, that the Rich man in Hell-tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments complained moſt of the torments of his Tongue: <hi>Father Abraham,
<note place="margin">Luk. 16.24.</note> haue mercy vpon me, and ſend Lazarus, that hee may dip the tip of his finger in water, and coole my tongue, for I am tormented in the flame;</hi> as if hell flame were moſt fierce againſt an euill Tongue, and that moſt ſure to endure the ſame.</p>
               <p>Now,
<note place="margin">The bitter paines of Hell.</note> as there is no coale ſo hote and raging as the Iuniper coale, for
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:2272:71"/>ſo S. <hi>Ierome</hi> teſtifieth;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hieron. ad Fabiol. Plin. nat. hiſt. lib.</hi> 8.</note> and <hi>Pliny</hi> alledgeth a naturall reaſon of it, <hi>viz.</hi> the gum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie matter of that wood more then in any other tree: ſo (to proſecute the ſame Metaphor) <hi>Par nulla figura Gehennae;
<note place="margin">Mat. 13.42 Reu. 21.8. Heb. 10.27 Math. 3.12</note> There is no paines like to the paines of hell.</hi> This <hi>fire is a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace of fire, a lake of brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, a deuouring fire, an vnquenchable fire.</hi> The furnace whereinto the three children were caſt,
<note place="margin">Dan. 3.19.</note> being made ſeuen times hotter then it was wont to be, was exceeding violent. But how much more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely ſhall this furnace
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:2272:71"/>of hell fry, whoſe fire is infinitely hotter then that was? O! Who is able to dwell with this deuouring fire? Who can endure the fiery rage of theſe Coales? <hi>They are coales of Iuniper.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet dwell in it they muſt who are doomed to it,
<note place="margin">The per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuity of thoſe paines.</note> and ſo muſt an euill tongue. As there is no eſcaping of it, ſo no comming out of it. <hi>Iuniper coales</hi> (as <hi>Pliny</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth) do keepe in fire for a long continuance: yea,
<note place="margin">Plin. vt ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra.</note> ſome maintaine,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Libri Suffla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torii vt cita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur a M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro, in Pſal.</hi> 120.</note> that the coales made of Iuniper wood, being couered with aſhes, keepe in fire for a whole yeare together. But
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:2272:72"/>what is this to the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity of the paines of hell? There the <hi>Worme dieth not,
<note place="margin">Mark. 9.44</note> and the fire neuer goeth out; the fire ſhall neuer be quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched:
<note place="margin">Luk. 3.17.</note>
                     <note place="margin">Reu. 20.10</note> they ſhall be tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted day and night for euer and euer.</hi> This is the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the endleſſe affliction of an euill Tongue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:2272:72"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX. </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sentence of condemnation denounced againſt the naughty tongue.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>HAuing thus heard the vnruly tongue Indicted,
<note place="margin">A tranſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the doome of a falſe tongue.</note> Arraig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, Conuicted and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, what now remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, but that we apply it to the terrour of thoſe who offend herein; and for our direction, both in the vſe, and againſt the abuſe of the Tongue?
<note place="margin">Sentence denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And here firſt, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the premiſes may
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:2272:73"/>ſtrike a terrour into the hearts of thoſe who are guilty of the crimes of an euill Tongue, <hi>Lyers, Swea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, Railers, Backbiters, Slanderers, filthy Speakers,</hi> and all the reſt of that rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of wicked-tongued creatures: Alas, in what a fearefull eſtate are they? How odious in the ſight of God? How iniurious vnto men? What a ſcorne to the Angels? How ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequious to the diuels? And how liable are they vnto the dreadful curſes of almighty God, both in the life preſent, and that which is to come?</p>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:2272:73"/>
               <p> Thou lying tongue,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
                  <note place="margin">The lying Tongue.</note> which, like a falſe clocke, doſt runne too faſt, and ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for pleaſure, or for profit, doſt coine vntruth, conſider what wrong thou doſt, and into what miſery thou doſt thruſt thy ſelfe. Thou peruerteſt the vſe of ſpeech; thou abuſeſt the ſenſe of hearing; thou diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolueſt, as much as in thee lyeth, humane Societies; thou beareſt the image of the diuell; thou art worſe then a Thiefe; for thus the Wiſe man ſpeaketh,
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 1.20, 23, 24, 25.</note> 
                  <hi>A lye is a wicked ſhame in a man, yet it is oft in the mouth of the vnwiſe: A thiefe is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:2272:74"/>then a man accuſtomed to lying, but they both ſhal haue deſtruction to their heritage: the condition of liers are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſt,
<note place="margin">Pro. 6.17.</note> and their ſhame is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer with them.</hi> A lying Tongue is one of thoſe ſixthings which God doth hate,
<note place="margin">Pro. 12.22</note> and <hi>lying lips are abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination to the Lord.
<note place="margin">Pro. 19.5.</note> A falſe witneſſe ſhall not bee vnpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, and he that ſpeaketh lies, ſhall not eſcape: the tongue that loueth, or maketh lies,
<note place="margin">Reu. 22.15 Reu. 21.8.</note> ſhall be excluded out of the heauenly Ieruſalem, and ſhall haue his part in the Lake which burneth with fire and brimſtone, which is the ſecond death.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:2272:74"/>
               <p> And as for thee, thou <hi>Swearing tongue,</hi> which art ſwollen with oathes, as a Toade with venime,
<note place="margin">Mal. 3.5.</note> The <hi>Lord will come as a ſwift witneſſe against thee;</hi> And there is a <hi>Flying booke of curſe and vengeance,
<note place="margin">Zach. 5.2.4</note> which doth houer ouer thee:</hi> Thine oathes are regiſtred in the book of accounts, &amp; when the great day of reckoning commeth, they ſhall be ſet in order before thee, and laid vnto thy charge: Thou art reſerued vnto the day of deſtruction,
<note place="margin">Iob 21.30. Luk. 16.24.</note> &amp; the time will come when thou ſhalt be miſerably tormented in that flame.</p>
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:2272:75"/>
               <p> Neither maiſt thou hope to eſcape,
<note place="margin">The mock<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing Tong.</note> thou <hi>mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tongue</hi> who art tipt with flouts, ſcoffes, and skornes againſt thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.4, 5.</note> 
                  <hi>he that ſitteth in the heauens, ſhall laugh at thee: the Lord ſhal haue thee in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſion, he ſhal ſpeak vnto thee in his wrath, and vexe thee in his ſore diſpleaſure. Why then doſt thou iudge thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?
<note place="margin">Rom. 14.10.</note> Why doſt thou ſet at nought thy brother? we ſhall all ſtand before the tribunall ſeat of Chriſt.</hi> Then ſhalt thou be depiſed, who didſt deſpiſe others. Then ſhalt thou be a ſcorn to Diuels, which here didſt ſcorne
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:2272:75"/>thy betters. And we know who hath ſaid it, and hee will be ſure to performe it, that both the mocking tong, and the railing tong,
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.22.</note> and the wrathfull tongue is in danger of hell fire.
<note place="margin">The ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous Tongue.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Needs muſt then the ſlaunderous and backbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting tongue be in dreadful danger,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 64.3.</note> which tongue is <hi>bent like a Bow, and ſhooteth out as Arrowes bitter words.</hi> Thou wretched tongue art a very murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, and not a ſingle man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaier, but thou killeſt three men, as it were with one ſtroke:
<note place="margin">Pro. 25.18</note> In which reſpect <hi>Salomon</hi> the wiſe calleth
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:2272:76"/>thee,
<note place="margin">Pro. 25.18</note> 
                  <hi>an Arrow, a maule, &amp; a Sword. An Arrow,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of him that is abſent, whom thou woundeſt afar off in his good name, in his goods, in his friends: and ſometimes in his life. A <hi>Maule</hi> or <hi>Hammer</hi> to knock him, who receiueth thy ſlaunder, in the head, <hi>eius enimaurem dum inficis, animam interficis,</hi> whiles thou doſt infect his eare, thou doſt deſtroy his ſoule, caſting thereinto ſeedes of ſuſpicion, hatred and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt. Laſtly, to thy ſelfe thou art a <hi>Sword,</hi> in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying thine owne ſoule, by committing that ſinne
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:2272:76"/>which is moſt odious vnto God; for he which ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth his neighbour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde his backe,
<note place="margin">Leu. 19.14</note> commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the ſame offence, with him that raileth on the deafe,
<note place="margin">Deut. 27.24.</note> and is like him <hi>that ſmiteth his neighbour ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly,</hi> both which are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed; and therefore no maruaile though this bee ſaid to be that ſeuenth ſin which God doth abhorre:
<note place="margin">Pro. 6.19.</note> for there is no ſinne which maketh a man ſo like the Diuell as this doth, for from ſlaundering and backbiting hee hath his name DIABOLOS, which is a common name to him
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:2272:77"/>with ſlanderers: And as the Lord doth greatly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt this ſinne, ſo hee hath threatned grieuouſly to puniſh it,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.20 Pſal. 52.5. Ezek. 22.9.</note> not onely the tongue offending, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the eare abetting, and the place harboring, and that not in this life onely, but alſo in the life to come:
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.10.</note> for if <hi>Railers</hi> ſhall not inherite the Kingdom of God, much leſſe ſhall ſlanderers.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> In the ſame predicament art thou,
<note place="margin">The filthy Tongue.</note> filthy Ribald tongue, which like a ſinke doeſt runne ouer with ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſceane and vnſeemely ſpeech.
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.33.</note> 
                  <hi>Euill words corrupt
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:2272:77"/>good manners;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 12.36</note> And of <hi>eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry idle word which men doe ſpeake, they muſt giue an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count at the Day of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> If of euery idle word, then what ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the tongue that ſpeaketh wanton words, ſcurrilous words, &amp; filthy ſpeech? Better it is to haue no mouth, then to haue it thus polluted; better to be without a tongue,
<note place="margin">A caueat for the Tongue. Eph. 4.29.31.</note> then to haue it thus defiled.</p>
               <p>Wherefore the counſel of the Apoſtle is very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable: <hi>Let no corrupt communication proceede out of your mouth, but that which is good and edifying,</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:2272:78"/>
                  <hi>Let all bitternes, and wrath, and anger, &amp; clamor, and euill ſpeaking bee put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way;</hi> Which leſſon that we may the better learne, let vs take a briefe notice, firſt how we may rule our own Tongue; ſecondly, how wee may beare the wrong of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers vnruly tongue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:2272:78"/>
               <head>CHAP. X. </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The binding of the tongue to the good behauiour, with certain rules and directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>MAny and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent are the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes which haue beene written,
<note place="margin">The right gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and well orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of our owne Tongues.</note> both by Philoſophers and Diuines concerning the well orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and gouernement of the tongue, out of whoſe ſauory writings I will one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gather this little handful of <hi>Directions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That wee keepe our
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:2272:79"/>tongue in order, two things are principally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite: Firſt, a good <hi>Heart:</hi> Secondly, a good <hi>Eare.</hi> A good <hi>Heart</hi> is neceſſary to a good <hi>tongue,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Heart is the fountaine of ſpeech;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 4.23. Luke 6.45 Mat. 15.19</note> For, <hi>out of the aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of the heart, the mouth ſpeaketh:</hi> And if the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine bee defiled, the ſtreames that iſſue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hence cannot bee cleane: for,
<note place="margin">Iob 14.4.</note> 
                  <hi>who can bring a cleane thing out of that which is vncleane?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A good <hi>Art</hi> likewiſe is neceſſary to the keeping of a good tongue,
<note place="margin">A good Art.</note> for it is a matter of no meane skill
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:2272:79"/>to learne the language of <hi>Canaan:
<note place="margin">Eſay 19.18</note> Hee</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Iames) is a perfect man that can rule his tongue.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 3.2.</note> And the Wiſe-man ſaith: that <hi>A word ſpoken in his place,
<note place="margin">Pro. 25.11.</note> is like apples of gold, with pictures of ſiluer.</hi> So that, <hi>Hic labor, hoc opus eſt,</hi> This is a labourious la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, an Art of Arts, to rule the tongue.</p>
               <p>To the better learning of which Art,
<note place="margin">Rules for it.</note> two rules are to bee obſerued in all our ſpeech. Firſt, Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before we ſpeake: ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, Moderation in ſpeaking.</p>
               <p>Meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before ſpeech
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:2272:80"/>is very neceſſary vnto our ſpeech;
<note place="margin">Meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before ſpeech.</note> for the tongue is the meſſenger of the heart: therefore ſo often as wee ſpeake without meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the meſſenger runneth without his errand. This Meditation in this kinde is two-fold: Firſt, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the lawfulneſſe; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, concerning the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediencie of our ſpeech. Firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
                  <note place="margin">For the lawfulnes.</note> we muſt premeditate whether that which wee would ſpeake, bee lawfull to be ſpoken:
<note place="margin">Eph. 4.29.</note> 
                  <hi>Let no cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt communication proceed out of your mouthes:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 34.13</note> Keepe thy tongue from euill, and thy lips that they ſpeake no
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:2272:80"/>guile.</hi> Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
                  <note place="margin">For the fitneſſe.</note> we muſt premeditate, whether that which wee are about to ſpeake, be fit to be ſpoken in regard of time, place,
<note place="margin">Pro. 10.32</note> and perſon: For, <hi>the lip of the righteous will know what is acceptable.
<note place="margin">Pro. 12.23.</note> A wiſe man concealeth knowledge, and he that hath knowledge, ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth his words;</hi> yea,
<note place="margin">Pro. 17.27.</note> 
                  <hi>euen a foole, when he holdeth his peace, is counted wiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The next thing requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the Art of Spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, is Moderation;
<note place="margin">Moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in ſpeech.</note> for this cauſe God hath giuen man but one Tongue, with two Eares, to teach him he ſhould bee more ready
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:2272:81"/>to heare then to ſpeake;
<note place="margin">Lam. 1.19.</note> he hath alſo placed it within, and guarded it with a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hedge, one of fleſh, another of bone, and moreouer, hath bound it with a bridle to the breſt; By all theſe, recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto vs Moderation of ſpeech: which Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration doth require theſe three properties in our ſpeech: 1. Truth: 2. Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie: 3. Modeſty.</p>
               <p>For the firſt;
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> we ought ſo to moderate our ſpeech,
<note place="margin">Truth of Speech.</note> that wee ſpeake nothing but the truth; A good tongue will <hi>ſpeak the truth from the heart,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 15.3. Pro. 3.5.</note> and a righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:2272:81"/>man hateth lying words:</hi> And,
<note place="margin">Pro. 12.19</note> 
                  <hi>the lip of truth ſhall be eſtabliſhed for euer.</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, when we ſpeak,
<note place="margin">Charity in Speaking. 1. Cor. 16.14. 1. Cor. 13.4, 5, 6, 7.</note> Charity muſt guide our ſpeech; <hi>Let all your things bee done in loue:</hi> And this <hi>loue, or charity, ſuffereth long, is kinde, enuieth not, vaunteth not her ſelfe, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth all things, beleeueth all things, hopeth all things, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth all things.</hi> Laſtly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Modeſty is required to the moderation of our ſpeech:
<note place="margin">Modeſtie in ſpeech.</note> 
                  <hi>A wholeſome tongue is a tree of life, but peruerſneſſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is a breach in Spirit, Pro.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 15.4.</note> 15.4. Therefore the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle requireth, that our
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:2272:82"/>ſpeech be gracious,
<note place="margin">Col. 4.16. Tit. 3.2.</note> vncor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, and full of meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
               <p>Theſe few caueats be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well obſerued,
<note place="margin">The bene fit of kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping a good tongue.</note> the Tongue more eaſily will bee ordered, and he that can do this, ſhall reape an incomparable benefite by it:
<note place="margin">Pro. 18.21.</note> For, <hi>Life and death are in the power of the tongue:</hi> And,
<note place="margin">Pro. 21.23. Pſal. 34.12 13. 1. Pet. 3.10</note> 
                  <hi>Whoſoeuer keepeth his mouth, keepeth his ſoule from euill.</hi> And therefore wee are ſo often in the book of God, called to the practice of it: <hi>What man is he that deſireth life, and loueth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny daies, that he may ſee good, keep thy tongue from
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:2272:82"/>euill, and thy lips that they ſpeake no guile.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But what man is able of himſelfe to obſerue this?
<note place="margin">None can do it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Gods ſpeciall helpe. Iob 39.37.</note> A man may lay his hand vpon his mouth, like <hi>Iob,</hi> &amp; ſtedfaſtly purpoſe, with <hi>Dauid,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 39.1.</note> that <hi>his tongue ſhall not offend,</hi> yet all in vaine, without the ſpeciall helpe of God: for,
<note place="margin">Pro. 16.1.</note> 
                  <hi>the gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the tongue is of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Therefore wee muſt pray to God for the well-ordering of our tongues. Eph. 6.19.</note> although he had an excellent gift for the well-ordering of his tongue, yet deſireth the <hi>Epheſians</hi> to pray for him, that <hi>vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terance might be giuen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:2272:83"/>him.</hi> And ſo muſt wee, if euer wee hope to haue comfort in the vſe of our Tongues, pray vnto God that hee would guide our Tongues, that hee would <hi>ſet a watch before our mouth,
<note place="margin">Pſ. 141.3.</note> and keepe the doore of our lips:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.15</note> And, that <hi>He would open our lips to ſhew forth his praiſe;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 19.14</note> So <hi>ſhall the words of our mouth bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies acceptable in the ſight of the Lord, who is our ſtrength and our Redeemer.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="153" facs="tcp:2272:83"/>
               <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How we are to put off an euill Tongue, when it goeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout in our hearing, to traduce and ſcandalize others.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>IF it bee a matter of ſo great difficultie to tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per our owne Tongue,
<note place="margin">A caueat for the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens Tongues.</note> much more hard and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult will it bee to tame an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other mans Tongue, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially where it claimeth a tranſcendent liberty vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it ſelfe.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 12.4.</note> 
                  <hi>With our tongue we will preuaile, our lips are
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:2272:84"/>our owne, who is Lord ouer vs?</hi> And yet this is a point of wiſdome needfull to be obſerued of vs, how to demeane our ſelues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an euill Tongue, and that in a twofold caſe. Firſt, when it concerneth others. Secondly, when it commeth more neerely home vnto our ſelues.</p>
               <p>And firſt,
<note place="margin">No credit to bee gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to an euill tong where it traduceth others.</note> when in our hearing it goeth about to traduce or ſlander o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, wee muſt be carefull not to giue any credit, countenance, fauour or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect vnto it in ſuch a caſe:
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:2272:84"/>for there is an expreſſe prohibition in the Law of God againſt it, <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.1.
<note place="margin">Exod. 23.1</note> 
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt not receiue a falſe report.</hi> And it is the aduice of the Wiſeman, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.21.
<note place="margin">Eccl. 7.21.</note> 
                  <hi>Giue not thine heart to heare all the words that are ſpoken, leſt thou heare thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant curſe thee.</hi> And in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place it is reckned as the property of a wicked man, to liſten to an euill tongue.
<note place="margin">Pro. 17.4.</note> 
                  <hi>A wicked man gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth heede to falſe lips, and a lyer giueth eare to a naughty tongue.</hi> And on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the Pſalmiſt doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord it as a note of a good man, &amp; of a citizen of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:2272:85"/>
                  <hi>that he will not receiue (or endure to heare) a falſe report againſt his neighbor.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 15.3.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides which expreſſe teſtimonies of holy writ,
<note place="margin">Why wee ſhould not giue any counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to an euill Tongue. 1. Cor. 13.4, 5, 6.</note> euidence of reaſon will e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince as much. 1. The rule of charity will require it: for charity <hi>ſuffereth long &amp; is kinde, charity enuieth not, charity thinketh not euill; it reioyceth not in iniquity, it beareth all things, belieueth all things, hopeth all things, endureth all things.</hi> 2. The rule of equity may enioine it,
<note place="margin">Mat. 7.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Whatſoeuer you would that men ſhould doe vnto you, ſo doe yee vnto them.</hi> Now there is no man that wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:2272:85"/>would haue another to receiue a falſe report in preiudice of himſelfe; and therfore <hi>Quod tibi fieri non vis, alterine feceris.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dictu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andri Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueri.</note> Do not vnto another, what thou wouldeſt not haue done vnto thy ſelfe. 3. The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuenience which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth many times from the receiuing of theſe ſiniſter reports, may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terre vs from hearing of them; for by this meanes many innocents haue bin brought into trouble and great diſgrace. <hi>Potiphar,</hi> being ſo credulous of his wiues report concerning <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> caſt him into pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:2272:86"/>
                  <hi>Dauid,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 39. 2. Sam. 16.3.</note> giuing too ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty an eare to <hi>Ziba</hi> his ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, wronged <hi>Mephibo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth</hi> in his goods.
<note place="margin">Heſt. 3.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Ahaſhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eroſh,</hi> vpon the hearing of <hi>Hamans</hi> falſe ſuggeſtions againſt the Iewes, cauſed a moſt cruell Edict to bee proclaimed for their vtter deſtruction. Infinite are the examples of thoſe, who by hearing of falſe to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gues, haue beene iniurious vnto others. 4. It is iniurious to our own ſoules, to giue any credite or counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to an euill tongue: for he whoſe eare is open to looſetongu'd creatures, becommeth acceſſary to
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:2272:86"/>their ſin,
<note place="margin">Hieron. Si deeſſet auditor, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracta tor.</note> and guilty of the ſame offence with them; for it is a true poſition, as in caſes of felony, ſo of ſlander, <hi>If there were not a receiuer, there would not be a purloiner.</hi> Yea in this caſe of ſlander there is more danger then in ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of felony: for a Theefe by himſelfe may ſteale, &amp; without a receiuer may rob his neighbour of his goods, but a Talebearer cannot rob a man of his good name, nor yet im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire his credite, vnleſſe there be another to heare and to admit his ſlanders: wherefore <hi>Bernard</hi> doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:2272:87"/>not to affirme, that Talebearers and Talehea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers are guilty alike.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bernard. de inter. Dom. Jdem de confid. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>in fine.</hi>
                  </note> And the ſame Author is very vehement in this point, <hi>Whether</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>a Tale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearer or a Tale-receiuer bee more dangerous and damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, it is hard to iudge: for the Talebearer hath the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell in his tongue, and the Talehearer hath the Diuelin his eare.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now that wee may the better keepe off the ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer,
<note place="margin">Remedies againſt the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of euil reports vnto vs.</note> and Talebearer, and ſo keepe our ſelues from beeing acceſſary to their ſinnes by receiuing their euill reports, there
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:2272:87"/>are three principall reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to be obſerued of vs, and to be oppoſed againſt them, who ſhall goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to trouble our eares with falſe reports.</p>
               <p>The firſt is a deafe eare:
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
                  <note place="margin">A deafe eare.</note> we muſt not afford an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill Tongue ſo much as the hearing, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.21.
<note place="margin">Eccl. 7.21.</note> 
                  <hi>Giue no eare, neither take heede to their words.</hi> A notable example to this purpoſe we haue in <hi>Geda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liab,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Ahikam, Ierem.</hi> 40.
<note place="margin">Ier. 40.14, 15, 16.</note> vnto whome when <hi>Iohanan,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Kareah</hi> had told in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret a conſpiracy of <hi>Iſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mael,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Netha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niah,</hi>
                  <pb n="162" facs="tcp:2272:88"/>that hee was hired by BAALIS, King of the <hi>Ammonites,</hi> to ſlay him; and often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times related this report vnto him, and that with great vehemency, <hi>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhould he ſlay thee, and ſo the Iewes which are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered vnto thee ſhall bee ſcattered, and the remnant in Iudah periſh?</hi> Although the report indeede was true (as afterward it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) and <hi>Iohanan</hi> ſpake in good will, and with an honeſt minde, yet <hi>Gedali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi> good man, not ſuſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting any ſuch attempt, hoping the beſt, and Ioth
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:2272:88"/>to entertaine any hard conceit againſt <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> would by no meanes giue eare to this report, but ſharpely reproued <hi>Ioha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nan,</hi> and forbad him to ſpeak any more of it: <hi>Thou ſhalt not doe this thing</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>for thou ſpeakeſt falſely of</hi> Iſhmael. A no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table example for our imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; although not for improuident ſimplicity, yet againſt ouer-raſh cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulity, that we ſtop our eares againſt ſuch enchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, and ſhut them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the reports of an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill tongue.</p>
               <p>The ſecond remedy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:2272:89"/>the receit of an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill Tongue,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
                  <note place="margin">A frow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing look.</note> is a <hi>Frowning looke:</hi> for ſo ſaith <hi>Salomon, Pro.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 25.23</note> 25.23. <hi>As the North winde driueth away raine, ſo doth an angry counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance the ſlandering tongue.</hi> When the skie is full of clouds, and in all likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood ready to powre down their raine vpon the earth, if the winde change into the North, that Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne winde will ſcatter abroad the clouds, and ſtop them from breaking forth into a Tempeſt (and therefore it is called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the clearer of the skie:</hi>) Euen ſo, when a
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:2272:89"/>tale-bearer,
<note place="margin">Heſiod.</note> or ſlanderer doth come vnto vs with a cloud of many idle words, which he deſireth to powre in, as rain into our eares, a frowning counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and an angry look will put them off. To all euill-tongued creatures therefore, we ſhould ſhew our ſelues ſterne, as vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to defile our eares with their pollution: For (as <hi>Hierome</hi> well obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth) if <hi>with a ſilent coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance wee giue eare vnto the Tale-bearer,
<note place="margin">Hieron. ad Fab.</note> we ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage him to ſlander; but if wee heare him not with ſome ſhew of delight, hee
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:2272:90"/>will learne not willingly to ſpeake that, which hee ſhall perceiue is not willingly heard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third Remedy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the reports of an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill tongue,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
                  <note place="margin">A ſharpe reproofe.</note> is a ſharpe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe. It is the Apoſtles rule,
<note place="margin">Ephe. 5.11</note> that <hi>we ſhould haue no fellowſhip with the vnfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full works of darkeneſſe, but rather reproue them:</hi> As our Sauiour ſharply reproued <hi>Peter</hi> for his flatterie, bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him,
<note place="margin">Mat. 16.25</note> 
                  <hi>Auant, Sathan,</hi> for hee was an offence vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him: So ſhould we giue a ſharpe check to a ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous Tongue, bidding it, Auant, Sathan, for it is
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:2272:90"/>an offence vnto vs. If we cannot by countenance put the ſlanderer to ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, we muſt by ſpeech curbe his wicked tongue; and not that alone: but if they will not deſiſt, wee are to complaine of them; and if all this will not ſerue, wee muſt endeuour, according to our place and power, that reall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments be inflicted on them,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 101.5</note> according to that of <hi>Dauid, Pſalm.</hi> 101.5. <hi>Him that priuily ſlande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth his neighbour, I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus much briefly for our direction againſt
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:2272:91"/>the hearing of an euill Tongue, when before vs it is readie to traduce o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Now we are in the next place to conſider how wee are to demeane our ſelues, in caſe of euill reports againſt our ſelues.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="169" facs="tcp:2272:91"/>
               <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How to endure the ſtroke of an euill Tongue, when it concerneth our ſelues.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>EVery one is a better Phyſicion to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe:
<note place="margin">The diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of enduring an euill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our ſelues.</note> wee can better en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the ſight of other mens wounds, then feele them in our owne bodies. It is hard to carry our ſelues vpright in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of euill reports a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt others; more hard to endure them when they light vpon our ſelues; yet
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:2272:92"/>both theſe are to bee lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: and this latter the ſooner, that wee may the better performe the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</p>
               <p>A good man muſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour to endure an euill Tongue,
<note place="margin">The duety for it.</note> and to carry him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe like a Chriſtian in the bearing of the ſame: For thus the Apoſtle doth ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh vs,
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 6.4.5, 6, 7, 8.</note> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. <hi>In all things approue your ſelues as the ſeruants of God, in much patience, in afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in neceſsities, in diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, in ſtripes, in impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in tumults, inlabours, in watchings, in fastings, by pureneſſe, by knowledge, by
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:2272:92"/>long ſuffering, by kindneſſe, by loue vnfeigned, by the word of truth, by the power of God, by the armour of righteouſneſſe on the right hand, and on the left, by ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and diſhonour, by euill report and good report.</hi> An excellent leſſon for our imitation, yet hard to bee learned, by reaſon of our inbred corruption: And therefore that we may the ſooner bee brought to the practice of it, theſe foure vertues are neceſſarily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired: firſt, <hi>Patience:</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <hi>Experience:</hi> third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Meditation:</hi> fourthly, <hi>Prouidence.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="172" facs="tcp:2272:93"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Patience</hi> is a principall Antidote againſt an euill tongue;
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
                  <note place="margin">Patience.</note> for ſo our bleſſed Sauiour doth aduiſe vs, <hi>Math.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 21.19</note> 21.19. <hi>In patience poſſeſſe your ſoules:</hi> And the Apoſtle <hi>Iames, Bee yee patient vnto the comming of the Lord,
<note place="margin">Iam. 5.7.</note> Iam.</hi> 5.7. There is no ſuch ſalue againſt the wound of a skolding tongue, a railing tongue, a ſlanderous tongue, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other kinde of wicked tongues, as <hi>Patience: Hee that is patient</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>) <hi>is a man of great vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 14.29.</note> And againe, <hi>Hee that is ſlow to anger,
<note place="margin">Pro. 16.32</note> is better then the mighty: and
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:2272:93"/>hee that ruleth his owne ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, is better then he that conquereth a Citie.</hi> This <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience</hi> is like vnto the Tree which <hi>Moſes</hi> caſt into <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rahs</hi> Spring,
<note place="margin">Ex. 25.25.</note> and it ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the bitterneſſe of the waters: It is like <hi>Ionathans</hi> Armour-bearer,
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 14.</note> which helped him to vanquiſh all his enemies.</p>
               <p>That <hi>Patience</hi> is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent vertue,
<note place="margin">The way to get pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience.</note> and an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute remedy againſt the poyſon of an euill tongue, no man can deny. But ſome, peraduenture, will reply, How ſhal we get this patience? How is it poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to retaine it, when a
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:2272:94"/>man is thus virulently ſmitten with the tongue? I anſwer with <hi>Salomon; A ſound ſpirit will beare this infirmity.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 19.14.</note> And to the bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of ſuch an infirmitie there had need be a ſound ſpirit: It is not for euery meacocke, for euery com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon man, to bee endued with it, but (as the Spirit ſaith) <hi>This is the patience of Saints;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reu. 14.12</note> as if none but Saints could haue it, and all they who are Saints on earth, and would be Saints in heauen, may not bee without it. To the procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and retaining of which Patience, there are
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:2272:94"/>required theſe foure pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties: Firſt, <hi>A deafe Eare;</hi> ſecondly, <hi>A ſilent Tongue;</hi> thirdly, <hi>A quiet Heart;</hi> fourthly, <hi>a good Conſcience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hee who would haue patience,
<note place="margin">A deafe Eare.</note> and therewith re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell the blow of an euill tongue, muſt carry about him a Deafe Eare, and not heare, at leaſtwiſe ſeeme not to heare the words of a malicious Tongue. An excellent preſident where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we haue in <hi>Dauid,</hi> who from his owne practice doth commend vnto vs this courſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38.13, 14.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 38.13 15.</note> 
                  <hi>They that ſeeke after my life</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>laid ſnares for
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:2272:95"/>me, they that ſought mine hurt, ſpake miſchieuous words against me; but I as a deafe man heard not.</hi> And againe in the next verſ: <hi>Thus I was as a man that heareth not.</hi> The like example we haue in the Heathen <hi>Ariſtides,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ariſtides.</note> who being reuiled by a railing tongue, went his way as if he had taken no notice of it; and being fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prouoked by his inſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting enemy raging and rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling againſt him in this maner; <hi>Why doſt thou haſte away? tarry, Ariſtides, and heare me:</hi> made this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere vnto him; <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I go away, becauſe how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:2272:95"/>thou haſt the power of ſpeaking, yet I haue not the power of hearing.</hi> The like is reported of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> who to one that with bitter words and reproaches did prouoke him, turned away his eares from him, with this reply: <hi>If thou canſt not bee maſter ouer thy Tongue, yet will I be maſter ouer mine Eares.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The next property of <hi>Patience is a ſilent tongue,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A ſilent Tongue.</note> when wee are euill ſpoken of, to make no reply. And this practice doth holy <hi>Dauid</hi> commend vnto vs in the aboue quoted place,
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:2272:96"/>
                  <hi>I was</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>as a dumbe man that opened not his mouth,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 38.14.</note> as one in whoſe mouth are no reproofes:</hi> which his patient ſilence and ſilent patience did notably ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt himſelfe in his mild behauiour towards railing <hi>Shimei,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Sam. 16.7, 8, 9, 10, 11.</note> when moſt traito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly and trecherouſly that vile monſter did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile him; albeit hee was egged on by <hi>Abiſhay</hi> to be auenged on him, yet wee heare no other reply of his but this: <hi>What haue I to doe with you, yee ſonnes of Zeruiah? let him alone; let him curſe, for the Lord hath bidden him.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="179" facs="tcp:2272:96"/>
               <p> The like example of ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence againſt an euill Tongue wee may behold in <hi>Saul,</hi> who when he was anointed ouer be King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and all the people whoſe heart God had tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, did ſo acknowledge him, <hi>yet ſome children of</hi> Belial <hi>ſcoffed at him,
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 10.27.</note> and deſpiſed him, and ſpake re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prochfull ſpeeches of him.</hi> Againſt all which the text noteth this to his ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar commendation. <hi>But Saul held his peace, or was as one that tooke no notice of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A third thing required vnto <hi>Patience is a quiet
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:2272:97"/>heart,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A quiet heart. 1. Pet. 3.4.</note> which thing (as the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh) <hi>in the ſight of God is much eſteemed;</hi> a property vnto patience very neceſſary: for <hi>from whence come wars,
<note place="margin">Iam. 4.1.</note> and fightings, and diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents? Come they not hence, euen from the luſts which fight in our members?</hi> Now although wee craue not that Stoicall apathie to be quite void of paſſions, yet wee muſt labour to curbe our paſſions, that they bee not too much ſtirred vp to diſdaine or reuenge. <hi>Say not in thy heart,
<note place="margin">Pro. 20.22</note> I will recompence euill for cuill:</hi> but imitate the Example
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:2272:97"/>of examples, Ieſus Chriſt the Sauiour of our ſoules, <hi>who when He was reuiled,
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.21</note> reuiled not againe, when He ſuffered, threatned not, but committed himſelfe to him who iudgeth righteouſly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly,
<note place="margin">A good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</note> vnto <hi>Patience</hi> there is required a good Conſcience; for where the Conſcience can plead In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, there Patience will worke moſt effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. This was <hi>Pauls</hi> Armor of proofe againſt all euill Tongues. <hi>Our reioycing</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.12.</note> (ſaith he) <hi>is this, the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of our Conſcience, that in ſimplicity and godly ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, not in fleſhly wiſedome,
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:2272:98"/>but by the grace of God wee haue had our conuerſation in the world:</hi> which is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the common practiſe of the world, where wee dayly heare theſe and ſuch like ſpeeches, <hi>If it were true, if I were guilty of that whereof I am accuſed, it would neuer grieue mee; but becauſe it is altogether falſe, therefore it grieueth me at the very heart:</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Apoſtles rule is quite contrary: <hi>It is</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>thanks-worthy, if a man for conſcience towards God endure griefe, ſuffering wrongfully; what glory is it,
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.19 20.</note> if when yee bee buffeted for
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:2272:98"/>your faults, ye take it patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? but if when ye doe well, and ſuffer for it, ye take it patiently, this is acceptable to God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The next Remedy (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides Patience) againſt the hurt of an euil tongue,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
                  <note place="margin">Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</note> is Experience, the very daughter (as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh) of Patience.
<note place="margin">Rom. 5.4.</note> Now Experience in this caſe may bee applyed to a threefold obiect. Firſt, to the quality of an euill Tongue. Secondly, to the commonneſſe of the erime. Thirdly, to the commodity which wee may reape thereof.</p>
               <pb n="184" facs="tcp:2272:99"/>
               <p> The quality,
<note place="margin">Of the quality of ill-toungd people. 2. Sam. 23.26. 1. Sam. 10.27. Ioh. 8.44. Pſal. 69.12 Pſal. 59.7.</note> or condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe who ſmite vs with the tongue, may teach vs good experience, and by conſequence work within vs patience: for, what are they for the moſt part, that whet their tongues with ſlanders? Are they not wicked people? ſons of Belial, vnthrifts, children of the diuell, Drunkards, Dogs? Now then conſider thus with thy ſelfe. <hi>Shall I be offended with euery dog that barketh at mee? Shall I reſpect a Drunkards tale? Shall I fret at an vnthriſts tongue? Let them go as they are, I will
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:2272:99"/>not care for them, nor for their words: For, can a man expect Grapes of Thornes, or Figs of Thiſtles?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe,
<note place="margin">Of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monneſſe of this triall. 1. Cor. 10.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Experience</hi> may guide vs to take notice of the commonneſſe of this triall. <hi>There doth no temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation herein ouertake vs, but ſuch as is common vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to man:</hi> yea, which is moſt common vnto the beſt men; for the beſt are moſt ſmitten with the tongue. And therefore our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our giueth this comfort and counſell vnto vs; <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are yee, when men ſhall reuile you and perſecute you, and ſhall ſay all manner of
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:2272:100"/>euill againſt you falſly for my ſake,
<note place="margin">Math. 5.11.12.</note> reioyce and be glad, for great, is your rewand in heauen; for ſo perſecuted they the Prophets which were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this is another fruit of experience,
<note place="margin">Of the commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thereof.</note> which may ſweeten the bitternes of an euill tongue vnto vs, when we do conſider the good which from theſe kind of trials will redound vnto vs;
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.1.</note> For, <hi>Howſoeuer no tryall for the preſent ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to bee ioyous, but grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous, yet afterward it yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the peaceable fruits of righteouſneſſe to them that are exerciſed thereby.</hi> And
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:2272:100"/>we know who hath ſaid, that,
<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.12</note> 
                  <hi>All they who would liue godly in Chriſt Ieſus, ſhall ſuffer perſecution.</hi> And this wrong which is offered by the Tongue, is a kinde of perſecution, witneſſe the Apoſtle, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.29. Now then, thus conſider with thy ſelfe when thou art wronged by an euill tongue;
<note place="margin">Gal. 4.29.</note> 
                  <hi>VVhat am I the worſe? what is mine aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie the better for theſe diſtaſtefull ſpeeches: If it be true which hee reporteth, I may reape a benefite by his tongue, to ſee my fault and to amend it; if it be falſe, what need I grieue at it? Good
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:2272:101"/>men will not beleeue it, euill mens cenſures I regard not; my Witneſſe is in heauen, He will defend mine innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, Hee will cauſe all this to turne to the best vnto mee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And certainely this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Meditation</hi> with our ſelues,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
                  <note place="margin">Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> is a ſingular good remedie againſt the mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of an euill Tongue; wherein remember this ſhort direction:
<note place="margin">M. <hi>Gren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> in his Sermon of a good name.</note> Doſt thou endure the ſmart of an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill tongue? Firſt, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with thy ſelfe, whether that whereof thou art ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed be good or euill: if good, then there is cauſe
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:2272:101"/>to reioyce in it, and not to grieue; if euill, then go a degree further, to finde out whether it be for ſome euill worke which thou haſt committed, or for ſome occaſion which thou haſt giuen: If it bee for ſome euill done, then ſee whether it hath wrought in thee the true ſorrow for that ſinne; whether thou takeſt this as a correction from God; and whether it leadeth thee to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: If it bee vpon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion onely giuen vpon ſuſpition; Then conſider with thy ſelfe thy frailty in offering the occaſion, and
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:2272:102"/>the mercy of God who hath kept thee from that euill, and doth by this meanes warne thee to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of giuing the like oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion.</p>
               <p>I will adde to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that golden medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Seneca;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Senec. de J<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra. c.</hi> 23. <hi>&amp;</hi> 24.</note> Let euery man</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>when he is prouoked by others euill words, thus ſay within him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; Am I mightier then</hi> Philip, <hi>that mighty</hi> Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donian? <hi>yet he was wronged with the tongue of a Peaſant, and would not take notice of it. Can I do more in mine own defence then</hi> Auguſtus, <hi>who had the taxing of the
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:2272:102"/>whole world? yet he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to winke at the tongue that taxed him. Why ſhould I ſo take to heart a few euill or idle words? Who am I that I may not bee ſpoken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt? Many haue pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned their enemies; ſhall not I forgiue a few fooliſh ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches? If he bee a youth who doth thus traduce mee? his age may excuſe him; If a woman? her ſexe; If a ſtranger? his liberty; If a familiar? his acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance may ſeeme to priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge him. Is this the firſt time that hee hath thus of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended? it may bee he hath often pleaſed. Hath he vſed
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:2272:103"/>this liberty of a lewd tongue a long time? we may the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter endure that, to which we haue becne long inured. Is hee a friend? hee did what hee would not. Is hee an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie? hee hath done no more then wee might well expect. If hee bee wiſe, let mee yeeld to him; if a foole, let me par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don him. The very beſt are not without their blemiſhes: There is no man ſo circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, but may ſometimes bee tript; none ſo faultleſſe, but may faile.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The laſt remedy againſt an euill tongue is Proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
                  <note place="margin">Proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</note> and that two waies: firſt, for the getting: ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:2272:103"/>for the keeping of a good name. The right prouident courſe to get a good name is, firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
                  <note place="margin">To get a good name.</note> to bee carefull to auoid all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, both outward and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, ſecret and open, great and ſmall: for, <hi>as dead flyes cauſe to ſtinke and putrifie the ointment of the Apothecary,</hi> ſo doth ſinne, ſeeme it neuer ſo ſmall, crack the credit of a man,
<note place="margin">Eccl. 10.5.</note> and expoſe him to the talke of tongues: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he who would not be euill ſpoken of, muſt bee iealous of his own doings, and not onely refraine from euil, but alſo abſtain
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:2272:104"/>from the very appearance of euill.
<note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 5.22.</note> 2. He who would auoid the hurt of an euill Tongue, muſt not onely abſtaine from euill, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo be plentifull in well-do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: for there is no way more ready for a good name then good workes, according to that of our Sauiour,
<note place="margin">Math. 5.16</note> 
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.16. <hi>Let your light ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee your good workes, and glorifie your heauenly Father.</hi> And to this purpoſe the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle doth aduiſe vs,
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.12</note> to <hi>haue our conuerſations honeſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Gentiles, that whereas they ſpeake againſt
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:2272:104"/>vs as euill doers, they may by our good workes, which they behold, glorifie God in our behalfe.</hi> Now becauſe it is a matter of as great importance to keepe a good name, as to get it, therefore hee who would ſtop the toung of the ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer, muſt bee carefull to vſe the beſt meanes to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue his credite and repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The meanes to keep a good name,
<note place="margin">To keep a good name.</note> are in effect the ſame whereby a good name is gotten; and therefore I will ſhut vp this caueat in a word, with that heauenly counſell of holy <hi>Dauid: What man is
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:2272:105"/>hee that deſireth life,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 34.12, 13.</note> and loueth many daies, that hee may ſee good, keep thy tongue from euill, and thy lips that they ſpeake no guile; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from euill, and doe good; ſeeke peace, and enſue it.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="197" facs="tcp:2272:105"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Concluſion of the whole Treatiſe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THus haue we heard this vnruly mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of our Bodie,
<note place="margin">A briefe repetition of all the Premiſes.</note> the <hi>Tongue,</hi> Arraigned, Indicted, Examined, and found guilty; Sentence of iudgement hath paſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, and order hath beene taken for the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the ſame: what now remaineth, but that euery one who doth wiſh well vnto himſelfe, ſhould well looke vnto himſelfe,
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:2272:106"/>that this naughty Tongue be not found within him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. <hi>Dauids</hi> care, ſhould be euery good mans caue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 39.1.</note> 
                  <hi>I ſaid, I will take heed to my wayes, that I offend not with my tongue.</hi> A leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon which <hi>Pambo</hi> was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares a learning, and yet, as himſelfe profeſſeth, hee could neuer through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly learne. And indeed, who can ſo well obſerue it as he ſhould?
<note place="margin">Iam. 3.2.</note> S. <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith, that <hi>if any man ſin not in word, hee is a perfect man, able to bridle all the bodie.</hi> O let vs labour and ſtriue for this perfection: And becauſe it is a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:2272:106"/>exceeding the power and skill of man, ſo well as hee ought to guide and rule his Tongue, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee are earneſtly to begge it at the hands of God;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 141.3. Pſal. 51.15.</note> that <hi>Hee would ſet a watch before our lips, and keepe the doore of our mouth;</hi> That hee would open our lips when they ſhould bee open, and ſhut them when they ſhould be ſhut; that hee would giue the right vtterance vnto vs, that ſo both the <hi>thoughts of our heart,
<note place="margin">Ephe. 6.19</note> and the words of our mouth might alwaies bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable in his ſight,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.14</note> who is our Strength and our Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</hi>
                  <pb n="200" facs="tcp:2272:107"/>The like courſe wee likewiſe are to take againſt the iniurie of other mens tongues; that ſeeing it is ſo difficult a thing to tame an euill Tongue, ſo grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous to endure it, and ſo impoſſible to auoide it, we ſhould therefore haue recourſe vnto almighty God, by hearty prayer, that he would preſerue vs againſt it, and teach vs true wiſedom to beare and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure it. Yea, O Lord, vouchſafe vnto vs both ſanctified Tongues and Eares, that our Tongues may euermore ſound thy praiſes, our Eares euer be
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:2272:107"/>attentiue to thy will: make vs zealous for thy glory, patient in our owne cauſe, and keep vs from the ſtrife of Tongues; So we thy <hi>people,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 79.13</note> and the ſheep of thy paſture ſhall praiſe thee for euer, and from generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to generation ſet forth thy Glory.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
